<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatise of the nobilitie of the realme collected out of the body of the common law, with mention of such statutes as are incident hereunto, upon a debate of the Barony of Aburgavenny : with a table of the heads contained in this treatise.</title>
            <title>Magazine of honour</title>
            <author>Bird, William, 17th cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 195 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 81 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A28196</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B2956</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18509</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12258158</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12258158</idno>
            <idno type="VID">57614</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A28196)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 57614)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 167:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatise of the nobilitie of the realme collected out of the body of the common law, with mention of such statutes as are incident hereunto, upon a debate of the Barony of Aburgavenny : with a table of the heads contained in this treatise.</title>
                  <title>Magazine of honour</title>
                  <author>Bird, William, 17th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 157 p. : ill., geneal. tables.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A.N. for Mathew Walbanke and Richard Best, and are to be sold at their shops ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Also published in the same year, with additions, as: The magazine of honour, or, A treatise of the severall degrees of the nobility of this kingdome; another edition appeared in 1658 as: Judge Dodaridge, his law of nobility and peerage, wherein the antiquities, titles, degrees, and distinctions concerning the peeres and the nobility of this nation are set forth ... according to the lawes and customes of England.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to W. Bird. Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Nobility --  Great Britain.</term>
               <term>Abergavenny (Wales)</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Sarah Wingo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Sarah Wingo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:57614:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:57614:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TREATISE OF THE NOBILITIE Of the Realme.</p>
            <p>COLLECTED OVT OF THE BODY Of the Common Law, with mention of ſuch Statutes as are incidet hereunto, upon a debate of the Barony of <hi>Aburgavenny.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With a Table of the heads contained in this Treatiſe.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>A.N.</hi> for <hi>Mathow Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banke</hi> and <hi>Richard Beſt,</hi> and are to be ſold at their ſhops at <hi>Grayes-Inne</hi> gate. 1642.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:57614:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:57614:2"/>
            <head>The Table.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>F</hi> Barons Page <hi>3.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The definition and deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Baron Page <hi>37</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the name Baron Page <hi>40</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Antiquitie of the Dignitie of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons, and the uſes of the Name. Page <hi>43</hi>
               </item>
               <item>If a Baron by Tenure grant the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour holden by Barony, whether ſhall the Grantee have the Dignity or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe? Page <hi>68</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Certaine Caſes wherein a Baron hath no priviledge Page <hi>127</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Noblitie and Lords in reputation, onely Page <hi>131</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Noble Women. Page <hi>132</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Honourable Women of three ſorts <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>adyes in Reputation. Page <hi>140</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:57614:3"/>
               <item>The Hypotheſis or particular queſtion, Page <hi>143</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Barony of <hi>Aburgavenny,</hi> a Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny by Tenure, and an ancient Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. Page <hi>145</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Line of the <hi>Haſtings,</hi> owners of the Caſtle of, and Barons of <hi>Abur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gavenny</hi> Page <hi>149</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Deſcent. Page <hi>156</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The family of <hi>Beauchampe L.</hi> Abur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gavenny <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:57614:3"/>
            <head>A Treatiſe of the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie of the Realme accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Law.</head>
            <head type="sub">Queſtion. Whether the Barony of <hi>Aburgavenny,</hi> with the title and dignitie be deſcended unto the Lady, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Daughter and Heire of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable <hi>Hen. Nevill,</hi> the late Baron of <hi>Aburgavenny,</hi> or unto the ſpeciall heire male, unto whom the Caſtle of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg</hi> being antiently the head of hat Barony is deſcended.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Herein are three things conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> Firſt this generall <hi>Theſis,</hi> whether within the Realme of <hi>England,</hi> there be any <hi>Baronies</hi> by Tenure, And whether <hi>Baronia ſit dignitas annexa <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>odo (vizt.)</hi> whether the heire male ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing the Castle holden <hi>per Baroniam</hi> ſhall
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:57614:4"/>have the title, or the heire generall which hath not the Caſtle.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> The ſecond is <hi>Hypotheſis,</hi> whether by former preſidents it may be ſhewed that this Barony of <hi>Aburg.</hi> hath beene guided by the lawfull deſcent of the Caſtle of <hi>Abur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gavenny,</hi> or whether the ſame hath gone to the heires generals ſundred from the Caſtle.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> The third is, that it is not to bee doubted whether the dignitie of Baron may deſcend to the heire female (for where ſuch Castles, <hi>&amp;</hi> is holden <hi>per Baroniam,</hi> and doth deſcend unto the heire female. There likewiſe the title, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as in many Noble houſes of this Realme is moſt evident) but The Queſtion is whether the title of Baron or Baroneſſe may deſcend to the heire fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male, whereas that fee holden by Barony, is deſcended to the Heire male or no, and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the fee to ſupport the dignitie may bee ſevered from the dignitie.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:57614:4"/>
            <head>A Treatiſe of the Barons of this Realme.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is true of <hi>Vlpian Publicè intereſt quod ordinum familiarum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſolva ſit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. O ſed ſi F. de ventre inſpiciend. Baldwin in la ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinis re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript Ante Nobilit. cap. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> Which duly conſidered, is cauſe that the ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all heire male of the late Baron deceaſed without any af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of honour or humour of am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition deſireth to make knowne what things former times obſerved, hee hath now found to have been conſidered in ſuch like Quaeries; Nevertheleſſe with all humility and loyall dutie hee ſubmitteth himſelfe to the princely pleaſure of the Queenes moſt excellent Majeſtie, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n whom is the fountaine of all Nobilitie, and unto the cenſure of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:57614:5"/>the right Honourable the Earle Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhall of <hi>England,</hi> unto whom the ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction and Cogniſance of the ſame cauſe by office appertaineth.</p>
            <p>But before proofe be produced,<note place="margin">1. By what law this Quer. is to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined.</note> it ſhall not bee amiſſe to conſider two principall things, what manner of proofe in theſe cauſes is moſt preg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and by what law this contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie might beſt bee determined. 3.<note place="margin">2. Touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſtate ofour B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies.</note> Some things are requiſite to bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered before in generall manner touching the ſtate of the Baronies within the Realme, whereby the Querie in hand may be the better ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended, and receive the more eaſie reſolution.</p>
            <p>As touching the firſt, it is to bee ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, that the dignity of a Baron, and that name given to a degree of Nobilitie, was not uſuall any where, untill neere the declination of the Rom. Monarchy, and therefore thoſe parts of the civill Law, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the ancient Roman lawes doe affoord ſmall proofe of the deciding of this kind of controverſie, otherwiſe then prechance now and then there
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:57614:5"/>are inſerted ſome generall ſentences or axiomes of the law of nature, which may be particularly applied as the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion ſerveth.</p>
            <p>Therefore in thoſe times upon the ſundry invaſions of thoſe Northerne people,<note place="margin">Goths. Vandalls.</note> which haſtened the ruine of the Romane eſtate, when Tenures and it which they call <hi>Feuda,</hi> had their firſt originall, divers new dignities of Nobilitie were deviſed, and drawne from the ſervice of the field, whereof ſome of them formerly had beene but names of Offices, as may appeare in the ſecond booke <hi>de feudis,</hi> in the title <hi>Quis dicatur dux Marchio,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Hee that would not have the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies moved within the Realme concerning this kind of Dignities to be deterined by the Common law, and yet would that the common cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of our Countrey ſhould direct the ſame, ſpeakes in my underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing contrary things, for it is a generall Maxime,<note place="margin">7. <hi>H.</hi> 6. <hi>Martin.</hi> 9. <hi>Ed.</hi> 4. <hi>&amp;</hi> 38 <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>Cuſtom. B.</hi> 59</note> that the <hi>Common cuſtome of the Realme, is the common law of the Realme.</hi> Therefore to affirme that the common uſage of the Countrey ſhould
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:57614:6"/>direct the controverſie, and to denie that the common Law ſhould deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine it is contrary to it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>That the common Law doth deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine this kind of Controverſie, it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſeeme ſtrange to him that conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the generall diviſion, whereby the ſaid law is diſtributed into parts,<note place="margin">Bracton, lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap <hi>5.</hi> &amp; <hi>2</hi> de ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſto &amp; jure.</note> 
               <hi>Eſt autem jus publicum, &amp; jus privatum. Jus publicum, Bracton</hi> diſpoſeth it, <hi>Eſt jus quod ad ſtatum Reipub. pertinet &amp; conſiſtit in ſacris Sacerdotibus &amp; Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtris.</hi> Others give a more large ſcope to this diviſion,<note place="margin">Ioachimus Hoſp. de ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris arte, lib. <hi>2.</hi> de rebus humanis ſive de jur' civil.</note> diſtributing <hi>jus publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum</hi> into three parts into <hi>Jus civile, jus fecile, &amp; jus queſtortum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt part <hi>jus civile,</hi> though it be the generall name of the whole Law, yet in this diviſion thye doe under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand thereby, that part of the Law wherein conſideration of many things are had, tending chiefly to the publick good, and wherein perſons of men are conſidered diverſly; <hi>Dividumtur quin<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> formae modis, pro loco, pro facultate, pro ordine, pro jure, pro dignitate.</hi> Under that diviſion which is in reſpect of Order, all degrees of perſons, Noble
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:57614:6"/>and ignoble are comprehended, and under the diviſion, in regard of digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty the Prince, Magiſtrate,<note place="margin">Pro ordine.</note> Officers of all kinds are contained.<note place="margin">Pro digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate.</note> The conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion therefore of all degrees of Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie is a part of the Law practiſed in every Kingdome, under that diviſion which reſpecteth publicke juſtice, and therefore in regard of perſons <hi>ſub or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine debito,</hi> this is now apparently perceived if we apply our thoughts to the regard of juriſdiction in generall, which reſpecteth the fountaine of ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice from whom it ſpringeth.</p>
            <p>All <hi>Juſtice</hi> is either <hi>commutatiue</hi> or <hi>diſtributive. Commutative Juſtice</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termineth debates growing upon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts, inheritance, or chattels, and thoſe bee reall or perſonall, which ſuites are commenced <hi>ad inſtantiam partis,</hi> by Plaint, Bill, or Writ, in the ordinary Court of Juſtice within the Realme. <hi>Diſtributive Juſtice</hi> is two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold, for either it doth ordaine pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment for ſuch crimes as doe fall within the correction of the lawes, or elſe it doth diſtribute a reward for vertues. That kind of <hi>Diſtributive
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:57614:7"/>justice</hi> that inflicts puniſhment pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth in ſome caſes <hi>ad inſtant. partis,</hi> as in appeales of Murder, Rape, Robe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That moſt uſually <hi>Ex officio,</hi> and that either by indictment or preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. That kind of <hi>Diſtributive ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice</hi> which concerneth the advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of vertue in beſtowing of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, which is the proper guerdon of vertue,<note place="margin">In Camer. ſtellat. <hi>39.</hi> El. z inter Comit. Kanc. &amp; Rotherom.</note> remaineth with the higheſt Soveraigne, annexed to the Imperiall Crowne of the Realme, for as vertue is the gift of none but God from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, ſo the reward of vertue with ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour for her Majeſtie, Gods ſubſtitute on earth within, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But when honour and armes (being the enſignes of honour) be once be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed on any, or poſſeſſed by any, if there ſhall ariſe contention betweene competitors for the ſame, pretending ſeverall challenge thereto the ancient policie of the Realme, hath ordained an eſpeciall Court,<note place="margin">The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Court of honour &amp; armes.</note> the juriſdiction whereof is immediately derived from the Crowne, and whereof the Judges have beene right honourable perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nages, <hi>The Lord high Conſtable,</hi> and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:57614:7"/>the <hi>Earle Marſhall,</hi> and in later times the Judge thereof is the Right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable the Earle Marſhall, the ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction of which Court conſiſts in the execution of that part of <hi>Diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butive Iuſtice,</hi> which concerneth the advancement and ſupport of Vertue.</p>
            <p>The Court wherein, and the Judges by whom theſe controverſies are to be determined by that which is above. ſaid may partly appeare. The Lawes whereby the ſame are to bee decided, are the Lawes of God, the generall concluſions of the lawes of Nature,<note place="margin">Diſt. lib. <hi>10.</hi> cap <hi>4.</hi> Com. <hi>304.6.</hi>
               </note> and of the law of Nations, together with the cuſtomes &amp; uſages of ſtatutes and Ordinances of our Countrey in like caſes heretofore, either obſerved, or provided, or which are the prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry grounds, and chiefe principles of the lawes of this Realme. And if no Cauſe heretofore hath happened that might bee a preſident to determine ſuch future Controverſies, then in the judgement of ſuch doubts, that reſolution is to be imbraced, which is moſt correſpondent to our govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment agreeable with the diſpoſition
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:57614:8"/>of our people, and ſo eſpecially as that the new judgement (ſo it be promul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged) doe not in any matter of conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence impeach, infringe, or infeeble any old or former received Law, or uſage then in force. The law there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of our Countrey ſo branched in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſeverall Courts, though the ſeverall Juriſdictions aforeſaid,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>8.</hi> Ed. <hi>4.</hi> per Yelverton, Bract. lib. <hi>1.</hi> Cap. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> ought to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine all civill and criminall Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes with the body of this Realme concerning whatſoever Cauſes.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſſe, ſome men there are not duly conſidering of what princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and parts the Lawes doe conſiſt, have laboured to prove that the Quae. of Nobilitie and Armes ſhould not bee determined by the lawes of the Realme, framing unto themſelves ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Arguments to prove their Aſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the chiefe of which arguments are here propoſed and anſwered.</p>
            <p> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>1</label> Firſt, it is ſaid that the Lawes of the Realme doe make all the Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters equally to inherit, but it is not ſo in the deſcent of the Dignities and titles of Honour, and therefore it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth that the Quae. concerning the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:57614:8"/>deſcent of dignitie are not determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble by the lawes of the Realme.</p>
            <p>To this Argument may bee anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,<note place="margin">Reſolve Bract. li. <hi>2.</hi> Cap. <hi>4</hi> fol. <hi>10</hi> &amp; li. <hi>2.</hi> ca. <hi>5</hi> fol. <hi>13.</hi> Coment. <hi>170.</hi>
               </note> that there are divers inheritances, ſome of things corporall, as lands, te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nements, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſome of incorporall fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, not by nature, but by mans policy, and therefore called <hi>Iura:</hi> the firſt ſort doe lie in Livery, the other are ſuch as doe lie in grant. Of the later ſort there are divers kinds, ſome matters of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptible profit, as Offices common, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Some others are matters chiefly of eaſe, as wayes and paſſages over the land of others; Some other con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne matter of profit and pleaſure, as Forreſts, Parkes, Chaſes, Warraines, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Others of juriſdiction, as the grant of Courts, others of Priviledges and immunities, as a getter to one and his heires, to be quit of Subſidies, Dizmez, Quinzems, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Others matter of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, as the dignitie of a Duke, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe, Earle, Viſcount, or Baron, granted to one and his heires gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, or to him and the heires of his bodie.</p>
            <p>Inheritance concerning matters of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:57614:9"/>honour,<note place="margin">Cap. <hi>1.</hi> Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terea de prohibita feodi alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natione per Frederes.</note> being things in their nature, participating of ſuperioritie and emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency, are not partible in any equali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie among many, and therefore muſt of neceſſitie deſcend unto one, and that is unto the eldeſt Daughter inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable, where there are no heires males lawfully to challenge the ſame.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>23.</hi> H. <hi>3.</hi> Fitz. Com. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>There was a Judgement in the time of <hi>H.</hi> 3. touching the deſcent of the Earledome of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> after the death of the Earle, who died without iſſue male, his Siſters being his heire, which Judgement was, that the ſaid Earledome ſhould be devided as other lands, and not to the eldeſt, But this Judgement was holden erroneous then. For <hi>Bracton,</hi> a learned Judge of that age,<note place="margin">Braction, lib. <hi>7.</hi> fol. <hi>76</hi> de Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſercen.</note> thus ſeemeth to write there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of <hi>(viz.) De hoc autem quod dicitur quod de feodo milit. veniunt in diviſione capital. Meſſuagia, &amp; inter cohaeredes dividuntur; Hoc verum eſt niſi capitale Meſſ. ſit caput Comitat. propter jus gladii quod dividi non poteſt, vel caput Baroniae caſtrum vel aliud aedificium, &amp; hoc ideo ne ſit caput in plures particulas
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:57614:9"/>dividatur, &amp; jura Comitat. &amp; Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niar' deveniant ad nihilum per quod de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiat regnum, quod ex Comitat. &amp; Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronibus dicitur eſſe constitutum. ſi au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem plura ſunt aedificia quae ſunt capita BAroniae dividi poſſunt in Cohaeredes fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta electione, ſalvo jum aſſuet. quia cum plura ibi jura ſunt quod liber per ſe po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terit inte gre obſervari, quod autem non eſt in uno ut praedoct' eſt licet à qui buſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam dicatur. Quod in alijs Regionibus aliquando de conſuetudine dividatur, ſed quod nunquam dividi videtur in Anglia debeat, nec viſum fuit contrar', &amp; erit conſuetudo regionis obſervanda ubi hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditas eſt quae petitur, &amp; perſonae naſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuntur quae petunt; Et unde ſi dicatur quod in regno Angl. aliquando facta fuit partitio, hoc fuit injuſtum.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vermon li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver d'an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquities à placitio, <hi>290</hi> ad placi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umt. <hi>301.</hi>
               </note> It is therefore evident that Baronies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> doe by the lawes of the Realme de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend unto the eldeſt Copercener, and Judgement given once to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Thereof <hi>Bracton</hi> doth rightly accompt to be unjuſt, his reaſon is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table; For in as much as the Honour and Chivalty of the Realme doth chiefly conſiſt in the Nobilitie, reaſon
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:57614:10"/>will not that ſuch dignities ſhould be divided among Coperceners, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by through multitude the reputation of honour in ſuch ſucceſſion,<note place="margin">Pet. Greg. de repub. lib. <hi>7.</hi> cap. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> and ſo divided might bee impaired, as the ſtrength of the Realme being drawne into many hands with decreaſe of livelihood by ſuch partition ſhould be infeebled. In which reſolution <hi>Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> the Baroned Biſhop of <hi>Hereford,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Britton, <hi>187.</hi> de he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. deviſ.</note> who compiled this Booke in the name, and by the commandment of <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. accordeth, who delivered this as a ſpeciall Caveat; <hi>En tous caſes ſont les droits des eſpees</hi> (that which <hi>Braecton</hi> calleth <hi>Ius gladij</hi>) <hi>gardes de ſole miſſe &amp; diſmembres,</hi> he calleth it <hi>Ius gladij,</hi> becauſe Dukes, Earles be at the time of their creation, <hi>Cinguntur gladijs gla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius autem ſignificat defenſione, reginae &amp; patriae;</hi> But howſoever that judgement was given, or whenſoever, it was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſſe very evident that it was ſoone redreſſed, for if it were given upon the death of <hi>Ranulph,</hi> the laſt of the name E. of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> who died a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 17. <hi>H.</hi> 3. the Writers about that time doe teſtifie, that the Earledome
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:57614:10"/>of <hi>Cheſter</hi> came wholly to <hi>Iohn Scot,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>David</hi> Earle of <hi>Hunting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> and <hi>Anguiſh</hi> and of <hi>Maude</hi> the el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt Siſter of the ſaid <hi>Ranulph.</hi> If it were given upon the death of the ſaid <hi>Iohn Scot,</hi> who died without iſſue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 24. <hi>H.</hi> 3. (for in the reports of the Law, the difference of a yeare is no great matter) yet notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſaid Judgement ſtood not in force,<note place="margin">Math. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris Monaſt. Sancti Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bani Chron. <hi>36.</hi>
               </note> for that the ſaid King aſſumed the ſaid Earledome into his owne hands upon other ſatisfaction made to the Siſters Coparceners of the ſaid <hi>Iohn Scot ne tanta haered tas inter Colos deduceretur.</hi>
               <note place="margin">M. <hi>6.</hi> H. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>That the deſcent of Dignities and Offices of Honour are determinable by the Common law is made manifeſt by the great cauſe concerning the office of the Lo. high Conſtable of <hi>England</hi> challenged <hi>tempore H.</hi> 8. by the Duke of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> and determined by the reſolution of the Judges, as by a note of that Caſe extant,<note place="margin">Dyer, <hi>285.</hi>
               </note> whereof my Lord <hi>Dyer</hi> in his Reports hath a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moriall is moſt evident where the Caſe ws that <hi>Humph de Bohun</hi> Earle
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:57614:11"/>of <hi>Hertford</hi> and <hi>Eſſex,</hi> held the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of <hi>Hatfield Newnham,</hi> and <hi>Whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hurst, in com' Glouc' du roy pur ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice de eant hault Conſtable d' Angl<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> mor' tyent iſſue</hi> 2 <hi>files que font particion de meſme les Maners, &amp; part le office eant ſervic' pur reaſon de tenure<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent' al ambu files de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e exerciſe pur lour ſufficient deputie (dum ſole' vixerint) mez aprez lour mariage, &amp; fuit de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e exerciſe ſolement pur le Baron el'eigne, Mes quia Hen. de Bullingb. Ca'ps H.</hi> 4.) <hi>
                  <expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ad eſpouſe le puiſne a <expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> le man' de Whittenhurſt de eant part' de terr' iſs' ten' fuit allot' pur ſa pur port.</hi> Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Querie was moved, whether by the unitie of parcell of the tenancy in the King the ſaid Office, were not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined, or whether this were in the other Siſter, which the Juſtices reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved that the Office had its continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in the eldeſt Siſter and her heires, of whom the ſaid Duke was diſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, but becauſe the exerciſe of the ſaid Office was a ſervice in reſpect of tenure, the ſaid Judges further reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved that the King might refuſe to have the ſaid office exerciſed, as any
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:57614:11"/>Lord may refuſe the homage of his Tenant; All which reſolutions the two chiefe Juſtices did ſignifie unto the King, according to the names of themſelves and the reſt.</p>
            <p> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>2</label> Second Objection that by the law of Chivalry, if the Widow of a Duke, Earle, Baron, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> doe marry with a Knight, Eſquire, or Gentleman, then nevertheleſſe ſhee retaineth her name of honour, whereas the Common Law doth otherwiſe determine there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and therefore they conclude that the common Law doth not determine this kind of controverſie concerning the title, names and dignities Noble.</p>
            <p>There muſt be made a diſ-Junction betweene the ſtrictneſſe of Law,<note place="margin">Reſolu.</note> and courteſie of Ladyes at the Court,<note place="margin">14 <hi>H.</hi> 6.2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 8. <hi>a.</hi>
               </note> for it is a rule in Law, as it is the ſame law of Chivalry, and in that point ſo is, and ſhould be knowne among the <hi>Heraulds,</hi> for aſmuch as a report of law in that caſe doth acknowledge it to be taken out of the bookes of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raulds,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>5.</hi> Mar. bre. Br. <hi>546.</hi> &amp; noſme <hi>69.</hi> Forteſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cue, <hi>100.</hi>
               </note> that <hi>Quando mulier nobilis nup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerit igncb.</hi> &amp;c. Of the which <hi>Forteſcue</hi> ſometime chiefe Juſtice of <hi>England</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:57614:12"/>yeeldeth a notable reaſon,<note place="margin">Cod lib. <hi>10.</hi> de incolis leg. ſinal.</note> 
               <hi>Mulieres honore maritorum,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ſin autem mino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris ordinis verum?</hi> For if ſhee be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured with any title in reſpect of her Husband, it is reaſon that after his death ſhe marrying with an inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our <hi>ſub cujus poteſtate vivet,</hi> that ſhe ſhould bee of like qualitie and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation as is her ſaid Husband. For as ſhe was inabled by the one, ſo muſt ſhe be content to leave that Nobilitie by ſtrict courſe of law for liue of the other, ſo that in this point the law is one way, and the honour and courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie of Ladyes another. And as the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilian ſaith in the like caſe,<note place="margin">6. <hi>E.</hi> 3.7. <hi>E</hi> 6.79. 3 <hi>Eliz</hi> 23.69.</note> 
               <hi>Aliud eſt jus, aliud Privilegium.</hi> Nevertheleſſe, the books of our law do make mention of that Courteſie, and allow of it as a Courterie though not as the Law.</p>
            <p>With theſe doe agree the law of Nation, with which concordeth alſo the Civill law, <hi>Foeminae nuptae clariſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis perſonis clariſſ. perſonarum appella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione continuentur.</hi> But of the other ſide <hi>clariſſ <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oeminarum nomine ſenator. Filiae, niſi quae viros claeriſſ. ſortitae ſunt, non habentur. Foeminis enim dignitat.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:57614:12"/>clariſſ. mariti tribuunt. Parentes verò donec plebeis nuptijs fuerint copulaetae.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cod de dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit. leg <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>tamdiu igitur clariſſ. foemina erat quaem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diu Senatori nupt. eſt. vos clariſſ. aut ſeparat. ab eo alij. inferioris dign. non nupſerit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nevertheleſſe,<note place="margin">Iacob Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buff ind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ct. leg. <hi>1.</hi> lib. <hi>12.</hi> Cod de dignitat.</note> in Kingdomes this holdeth not place in the blood Royall, for <hi>Si filia Regis nubat alicui Duci vel Comiti dicitur tamen ſemper Regalis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Likewiſe, the ſaid firſt rule touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Nobilitie of Women married unto perſons ignoable doth faile where they inherit thoſe dignities. For if a Dukedome, Earldome, or Barony de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend unto any woman, who taketh an ignoble man to husband, that husband ſhall not debaſe the wife, having ſuch Dignities deſcended, but rather he in her right ſhall beare the title of ſuch dignities eſpecially if he be intituled by the Courteſie.</p>
            <p> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object </seg>3</label> A third Object. is this, It is ſaid that by the law of Chivalry exerciſed within the Realme, if a Baron be crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted an Earle, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that the heire appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent of ſuch Earle, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſhall after ſuch Creation of his Father beare the title
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:57614:13"/>of the Barony, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but this is not uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all by the courſe of the Common law: therefore the deſcent of ſuch Dignities not to be guided by the Common Law.</p>
            <p>The common law doth not diſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low any ſuch uſage,<note place="margin">Reſolu.</note> for it being the cuſtome of the Realme, is the law of the Realme. Howbeit the Common Law doth put a difference betweene ſuch Heires apparent as carry thoſe Titles lawfully in reſpect of the uſage, and ſuch others as have them by Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or otherwiſe, for ſuch Heire ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent is no Peere of the Realme as thoſe by Creation, or ſuch as have the Earldome, <hi>&amp;c</hi> upon deſcent after the death of his Aunceſtor, and therefore as when the Lord <hi>Hen. Howard,</hi> Earle of <hi>Surry,</hi> Son &amp; Heire apparent to <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> Duke of <hi>Norfolke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">An Earle by Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity.</note> was attainted his Triall was by <hi>Iury</hi> of Knights and Gentlemen, not by Barons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for that hee was an Earle by Nativity, which in reſpect of tryall the Law doth not allow. The like tryal chanced to the Lord <hi>Gray,</hi> who 33. <hi>H.</hi> 8. was in B. K. arraigned of treaſon, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:57614:13"/>to bee tried by a <hi>Jury</hi> of Knights and Gentlemen, and not by Peeres, <hi>Cauſa qua ſupra;</hi> but he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed the Indictment and the Jury were diſmiſſed, yet ſuch ſhall hold precedency of place at Court, and in the preſence of their Soveraigne, as is uſuall in that behalfe.</p>
            <p> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obje. </seg>4</label> It is objected fourthly, that by the Common law a man may not bee cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Lord of that he hath not; But by the law of Chivalry a man may bee created Earle of a County, having no land therein: therefore differ.</p>
            <p> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reſol. </seg>1</label> It is true that ſome particulars of ordinary proceedings in the law doth differ from other proceedings con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Chivalry, and yet their diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence is no other, then as one hand doth differ from another, both are hands, and both of one body. That part of the law which concemeth pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porty, doth not allow a man to bee called Lord of that wherein he is no way owner in demeſne or ſeignory, but when you draw the law to the conſideration of dignity, the whole reſolution muſt reſt upon the Patent
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:57614:14"/>of creation,<note place="margin">Earle pur autre vie <hi>31.</hi> H <hi>6.29.</hi> pur Danby.</note> wherein the name is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed at the pleaſure of the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, for one may be Earle during the life of another, if the Creation be ſo.</p>
            <p> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> But I anſwer further, that it is not true that every Earle muſt be Earle of a place, nor every Earle of a place Earle of a County, nor that every Earle of a County, hath nothing in that County whereby he is Earle. For the better manifeſtation conſider that ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginally within this Realme Earl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Counties in the antient Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Saxon Governours were not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dignities of honour, but alſo offices of Juſtice,<note place="margin">Vea. leg. Edgar regis de Conſil. Lamb. <hi>80.</hi> n. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> for that they did further the adminiſtration of Juſtice in the County whereof they were Earles or Aldermen, they likewiſe had their Deputies under them, the Sheriffe an Officer, yet containing the name of his ſubſtitution in Latine <hi>Vicecomes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Camden. <hi>107.</hi>
               </note> Theſe Earles in recompence of their travailes received a Salary name by the third penny of the profits of the ſaid County, which continued long after the Conqueſt, and was inſerted
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:57614:14"/>as a princely benevolence in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of Creation, as by divers antient Charters may appeare, which after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward were turned into Penſions,<note place="margin">H <hi>3.</hi> dedit Haber<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o de burgo <hi>40</hi> pro <hi>3.</hi> deno. Com. Cant. de quoeund creavit co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit. habe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. ſibi, &amp; hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. de cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. uaeor Alexand. reg. Scotiae. <hi>13.</hi> H <hi>3.</hi> in turr. Lond. <hi>33</hi> H. <hi>6.29.6</hi> H. <hi>8.</hi> Dy. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> for the better maintenace of that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and as appeareth by a booke caſe upon the pleading of the Patent, whereby <hi>H.</hi> 6. Created that worthy Knight, Sir <hi>John Talbot</hi> Earle of <hi>Shrewsbury,</hi> which Penſion is ſo an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed unto their Dignitie, as that by any meanes of alienation it cannot be ſevered, and therefore in reſpect of ſuch Penſions which were the third part of the profits of the County, or other ſumme in lieu thereof, ſome have not without probabilitie imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, <hi>Quod Comites nominabant capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>end. fiſco Regis ſocij &amp; Comites fido par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipes eſſent Lamberd.</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Of the ſingle Ear. and not <hi>Palentine</hi> with <hi>Engl</hi> there have beene princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally two kinds, but every one of them againe ſubdivided into ſeverall branches, for either they take their names of a place, or hold their Title without any place. Thoſe that take their names of a place, are of two
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:57614:15"/>kinds, for either the ſame place is a County which is moſt uſuall, or elſe ſome other place and no County, as a Towne, Caſtle, or honour, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of which later ſort ſome are more anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, having their originall even from the Conqueſt, or ſhortly after: as the Earledome of <hi>Richmond</hi> in Yorkſhire. <hi>Clarence</hi> in Suff. <hi>Arundell</hi> in <hi>Eſſex,</hi> all which had their originall in the time of the Conquerours by donation of thoſe Caſtles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Earledomes of <hi>Bath temp. H.</hi> 7. <hi>&amp; H.</hi> 8. erected in the family where now it remaineth, and the Earledome of <hi>Bridgewater,</hi> whereof Sir <hi>Giles Dawbeney</hi> was Created Earle, <hi>temp. H.</hi> 7. Earledomes which have their titles without any place, are likewiſe of two kinds, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in reſpect of office, as is the Earle Marſhall, for it is granted in this or the like manner. <hi>Officium Comit. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſcal' Angl'</hi> with further words, <hi>(vizt.) A.B.</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Comit. Mareſcal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum Angl. creamus, ordinamus,</hi> &amp;c. by which it appeares that the very office is an Earledome.<note place="margin">Earle by birth.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond ſort are Earles by birth,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:57614:15"/>and ſo are all the Sons of the Kings of <hi>England,</hi> if they have none other dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie beſtowed upon them, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is ſaid that <hi>John</hi> afterwards King of <hi>England,</hi> in the life-time of his Father <hi>H.</hi> 2. was called <hi>Counte ſans terre,</hi> before he was affied unto <hi>Alice,</hi> the Daughter of the Earle of <hi>Morton</hi> in <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>5</label> A fifth Object. is this, The law of Chivalry proceedeth not in the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment of a combate in ſuch manner as is performed by the courſe of the Common law, either in the Writ of right by Champion, or in the Appeale by perſon, therefore the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naging of the cauſes in Chivalry is not in the common law eſpecially,<note place="margin">37. <hi>H.</hi> 6.36 37. <hi>H.</hi> 6.</note> foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as our bookes doe acknowledge them to be determined by courſe of the Civill law.</p>
            <p>It is true,<note place="margin">Reſol.</note> that the manner of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of thoſe ſeverall kinds of Combates is very different, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the combate for Honour, or upon the Appeale for treaſon be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed within <hi>England,</hi> according to the cuſtome of forraigne Nations in
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:57614:16"/>ſome reſpects, although not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſo, that almoſt every particular Countrey hath a particular manner, by meanes whereof ſome men ſeeing the difference betwixt thoſe and the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary courſe of obſervance of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates for land in the Writ of right, or for life in the Appeale of felony, have therefore imagined that the procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in Combate before the Lord Conſtable or Lord Marſhall in the Appeals of treaſon, or in cauſes of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour betwixt ſuch perſons,<note place="margin">Paris de Putio Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hannes de delignatio Iac. de Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilio And. Aſſiatus. Iul. Herret. Anthon. Moſſeus, Cod. lib. <hi>21.</hi> gladiatus lege unica. Dig lib <hi>9.</hi> ad legem aqualiam, leg. <hi>7.</hi> Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus Lipſius de gladiato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus.</note> as by the law may wage the ſame, ſhould be according to the courſe of the Civill law, yet nevertheleſſe it muſt been certaine that the Civill law of the Romanes, is ſo farre off from gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving any allowance thereto, as that it ſeemeth to forbid it. For that law of the Chriſtian Emperour <hi>Conſtantine</hi> is moſt notably alledged to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe by moſt of the learned Doctors of the Civill law, that have written <hi>De duello,</hi> the words of which law are theſe, <hi>Cruenta ſpectacula in otio ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vili &amp; domeſt. quiete non placent.</hi> And that which for diſputation ſake
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:57614:16"/>is alledged to the contrary. <hi>Si quis in colluſtratione vel pancratio vel pugiles dum inter ſe exercenturs alius alium oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cideret. Si quidem in publico certamine alius alium occiderit ceſſat, equalia, quia gloriae cauſa, &amp; virtutis non injuriae gratia vitetur damnum datum,</hi> is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood rather of Juſts and ſuch like playes <hi>de gladiatoribus,</hi> as were uſuall among the Romanes, all which were abrogated by this law of <hi>Conſtantine.</hi>
               <note place="margin">I. de Ligna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no de Duel. a <hi>5.</hi> Inlius Ferret. de duel. n. <hi>20.5.</hi> Andr. Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cicus de du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll, cap. <hi>4.</hi> de legibus Congobard, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it de Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchijs, n. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Iul. Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> de duel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o. <hi>17.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor. lib. <hi>48.</hi> cap <hi>161.</hi> n <hi>8.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>Nevertheleſſe among theſe war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Nations that invaded the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Empire this kind of ſingle Combate hath beene againe exerciſed in divers Kingdomes, according to the cuſtome of every ſeverall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey. Among the <hi>Lumbards</hi> it, was permitted in 19 caſes; Their wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons being nothing elſe but the Shield and the Baſton. And yet of the uſe, or rather abuſe therreof, the King <hi>Katharius</hi> ſeemeth to complaine, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing to have abrogated the ſome. <hi>Quia incerti ſumus de judicio dei, &amp; multos audivimus per pugnam ſine ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta cauſa ſuam cauſaem perders, ſed propter conſuetua. gentis noſtre Longo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bardor.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:57614:17"/>legem impiam vetare non poſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> In the ſeverall Kingdomes of <hi>Cicilie</hi> in <hi>Spaine,</hi> it hath beene allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in ſome Caſes; Likewiſe in <hi>France</hi> by the conſtitution of <hi>Philip le Beau. Anno</hi> 1306. Likewiſe the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour <hi>Fredericke</hi> did permit it in cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine caſes expreſſed in the Treatiſe <hi>De conſuetud. feodorum</hi> in the title <hi>De Pace tenenda &amp; ejus violatoribus ſi quis hominem, ſi quis alium, ſi quis Miles, &amp;c.</hi> In ſome places of <hi>Italy</hi> the battell hath beene allowed upon leſſe occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,<note place="margin">De pugn. cern. cap. <hi>4.</hi> in fine.</note> of the which <hi>Alciatus</hi> maketh mention with ſome deteſtation.</p>
            <p>Hereof it is evident that the order, manner, and cauſes of ſingle Combate are different in divers Countries, and every Countrey: that people follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their owne Cuſtomes and uſages being their peculiar Law: and in this our Realme, it was a tryall much more frequented in antient times neere the Conqueſt then ſucceeding ages, for it is evident by ſome antient Records and Plea rolls yet extant of King <hi>Steven,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Wager of battell in perſonall cauſes.</note> 
               <hi>H.</hi> 2. <hi>R.</hi> 1. and King <hi>Iohn,</hi> that it was permitted to be waged in
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:57614:17"/>perſonall occaſions in caſes wherein men now commonly wage their law,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>37.</hi> H. <hi>6.</hi> fol <hi>36.37.</hi> H. <hi>6.</hi> fol. <hi>20.</hi> Glan. lib. <hi>8.</hi> cap <hi>8.</hi> Que bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talle partee gage en aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cun caſe en vn' bre. de fac. Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> and therefore in 37. <hi>H.</hi> 6. and 37. <hi>H.</hi> 6. fol. 20. <hi>Needehams</hi> opinions are much more agreeable to the truth, where both doe affirme that ſuch waging of battell before the Lord high Conſtable and Earle Marſhall, is by the Lawes of this Realme, although it bee deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined before them, and ſo great a Sympathy is betweene that Court and others of common Juſtice, as that the Judges ſhall take notice of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings before the Lord Conſtable and Earle Marſhall upon occaſion of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered riſing in debate before them.</p>
            <p> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>6</label> The ſixth Objection is this, The common Law in the trials of matters in ſentence doth proceed by a Jury of 12. but the law of Chivalry in the triall of matters in fact concerning Honour and ARmes proceedeth upon examination of witneſſes, which is according to the courſe of the civill Law: therefore matters of Honour are to bee determined by the civill (not common) Law.</p>
            <p>I the tryall of matters in fact,<note place="margin">Reſolu.</note> the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:57614:18"/>common law doth not alwayes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed by a Jury, for although they moſt properly lye in the Conuſance of the Jury,<note place="margin">8. <hi>Ed</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> triall 94. 9 <hi>Ed</hi> 2. Iudg me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, 231.</note> yet in other matters the Law hath ordained ſome other man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of tryall, as they gage others by Witneſſes, as if a Wife bring a Writ of Dower, ſuppoſing her Husband to bee dead, and the tenant ſaith that he is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live, whereupon they arer at iſſue, this ſhall be tried by Witneſſes only, and not by Jury.<note place="margin">33. <hi>H.</hi> 6.9. 35. <hi>H.</hi> 6.47</note> So likewiſe if land be recovered by default, and after brings a Writ of diſcript, for that hee was not lawfully ſummoned in the former action, upon which they are at iſſue,<note place="margin">13. <hi>Ed.</hi> 1.36.37. 13. <hi>H</hi> 7. <hi>vill</hi> 43.47. <hi>H.</hi> 3 15. <hi>Ed</hi> 2. <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron</hi> 385. <hi>Vill.</hi> 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.19. <hi>H.</hi> 6.32.</note> this ſhall be tried by examination and depoſitions of the ſummoners, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and not by the Jury. In a Write <hi>de Nativo habendo,</hi> whereby the Plaintife claim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Defendant to bee his villaine, the Defendant ſaith hee is a freeman, and thereupon they are at iſſue, this ſhall not be tried by a Jury, but by Witneſſes, namely ſuch males as be of the blood and kindred of the Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant and not otherwiſe.<note place="margin">48. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>n.</hi> 34. <hi>H</hi> 2. 46. <hi>E.</hi> 3.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Some matters of tryall in fact are
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:57614:18"/>tried by view and inſpection of the Court,<note place="margin">8. <hi>Account.</hi> 121.</note> &amp; not by a Jury as the Nonage of the Plaintife or defendant alledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelfe to be within the age of twenty one yeares.</p>
            <p>And the like tryall is of a May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kem,<note place="margin">21. <hi>H.</hi> 7 33. 39. <hi>E.</hi> 3.32. 7. <hi>H</hi> 4.24. 38 <hi>E.</hi> 3 27. 18 <hi>E.</hi> 4 36. 2 <hi>H</hi> 4.17. 22. <hi>H</hi> 6.27.</note> wherras in an Appeale of May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kem the parties bee at iſſue, whether the hurt be a Maykem or no, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the Courts of the ordinary of ſome other Iudge or Officer, as in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſpirituall by Certificate thereof from the ordinary, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning matters done beyond the Seas in the Kings Army, or concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Combate for honour, armes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by Certificate of the Lord Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable or Earle Marſhall,<note place="margin">3 <hi>H</hi> 6.6. 48 <hi>E.</hi> 3.3.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> whereby appeareth the weakneſs of the former Argument, but in caſes uſuall the law alloweth the triall by Witneſſes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Iury; And therefore in the Lord Conſtable and Earle Marſhals Court matter in fact concerning Honour and Armes (which lie not in the knowledge of the vulgart ſorz) the the Common Law grounded upon the beſt reaſon would it ſhould be tried
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:57614:19"/>by witneſſes or matters of Record, as the cauſe ſhall require, and not that the ſame ſhould be tried by the conſcience of the vulgar people,<note place="margin">22. <hi>Aſſeſſ. pl.</hi> 24.</note> being matters whereof they have no knowledge ſufficiently to diſcerne.</p>
            <p>Hitherto have I wandred of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, to ſhew that our homebred Law is ſufficiently able, and ought to trie all cauſes civil (other then Marine) ſuch as are riſing with the body of the Realme (and not in forraigne parts) whereby appeared the excellencie of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law, which maintaineth the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular juriſdiction of every particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Court. For it is the common Law (through the ſundry Writs of prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition which it uſeth) which keepeth every Court within the compaſſe of his proper ſphere, and upholdeth the juriſdiction of the Court of the Earle Marſhall. By that therfore which hath beene ſaid, two things may ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appeare.</p>
            <p> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, that the Court of the Lord Conſtable and Earle Marſhall have had, and now the Earle Marſhals Court hath particular juriſdiction ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginally
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:57614:19"/>and primarily to determine matters of controverſie concerning Chivalry, Dignity, Honour &amp; Armes, and ſome other things acknowledged to belong to the ſaid Court by the Lawes and Statutes of our Countrey.</p>
            <p>Howbeit by a conſequent but not originally, ſome other Courts of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary juſtice may, as the caſe ſhall require, determine likewiſe ſuch like controverſies touching honour, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but not <hi>(eaſe or in ſua)</hi> but rather by an adjunct, as by this example may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare. If there bee two competitiours of a Barony, and during the time that their cauſe is litigious, the one of them is impleaded at the common Law by originall Writ <hi>Cap. alz &amp; plures</hi> in a perſonall action, and thereupon an exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent is awarded, whereupon inſueth an Outlary, the party outlwaed brings a Writ of errour, and aſſigneth for er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, that hee having ſuch a Caſtle to him deſcended, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> holden <hi>per Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niam,</hi> whereupon his Anceſtours have beene Barons, anp he himſelfe Baron, no Cap. ought to be awarded againſt him, but in very ſpeciall caſes onely,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:57614:20"/>therefore the outlary erroneous. This matter of errour alledged, the Court cannot conſider without due determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the title of the Barony, wherein if the Court of the Earle Marſhall ſhould adjudged one way by any forraigne Law in the ſame queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on depending there, and the Court of B.R. adjudge another way by the common law of the Realme: upon this Writ of errour, there would en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue thereof a great confuſion and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniencie in the Common-wealth, which the law will rather eſchew then any other miſchiefe whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever.</p>
            <p> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, therefore it doth appeare by the ſpeeches aforeſaid, that the common law ought to decide this controverſie, and that both Courts ought to follow one and the ſame law, in as much as the common law is more ample then ordinary reports of Caſes in the yeare bookes. For whatſoever is not diſagreeing from the law of God, and is conſonant to the lawes of nature and Nations, allowed by the cuſtomes of our
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:57614:20"/>Countrey not diſagreable to former preſidents anſwerable to all good learning is the vndoubted common law of the Realme, which know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth no other Author but God and nature, and whereof the Iuges in all ages have ever thought it honourable to receive all good helpes from every faculty of literature in the ending of difficulties queſtioned before them.</p>
            <p>The proofe therfore in this contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie to be produced ſhall be argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of reaſon,<note place="margin">What ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of proofes are to be uſed in your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies.</note> allegations of autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, preſidents of time drawne out of Records, Hiſtories, ouncient Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Lawes and cuſtomes of our owne countrey and furniſhed with ſuch other matters of neceſſary know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge as may tend to the better expla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</p>
            <p>It followeth ſomewhat to ſpeake in generall of the dignitie and degree of a Baron,<note place="margin">The 2. matters before propoſed.</note> whereby the Qu. in hand may be the better conceived and be reduced to a more cleere determinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which for order ſake I will re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>duce to the conſideration of theſe principall heads.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:57614:21"/>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>The definition or deſcription of a Baron.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>The Etimologie of the name of Baron.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>The antiquitie thereof, and the divers vſe of the name.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. <hi>The diviſion and conſideration of the ſeverall Kinds of Barons.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>5. <hi>The determination of certaine, Qu. and difficulties tending to the more manifeſtation of the natures of the ſeverall Kinds of Barons.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>6. <hi>And laſtlie a declaration of the divers and ſundry priviledges allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the lawes of this Realme unto the Barons and Nobilitie of the ſame wherin the vulgar,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>hath no participation.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Which things being diſcouered there will be laied open (as I doe conceiue) a plaine way to the finall concluſion and reſolution of the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion in hand.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:57614:21"/>
               <head>The definition or deſcription of a Baron.</head>
               <p>IT is a rule of Law that <hi>Om nis de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitio in jure periculoſiſſima.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dig. l. <hi>51.</hi> de regulis ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris <hi>203.</hi> omnis defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitio.</note> 
                  <hi>Rarum eſt enim ut non ſubverti poſſit.</hi> And therefore I doe not often ſee any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition or deſcription of a Baron. <hi>Baldus</hi> thus deſcribeth a Baron,<note place="margin">Baldus Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notus de ſectionibus.</note> 
                  <hi>vt ſit quiſquis merum mixtum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> imperium in aliquo Caſtro opidove conceſſione prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipes habeatur,</hi> But his ſeemeth ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther particular to ſome then generall to all, and therefore <hi>Alciatus</hi> vſeth theſe words <hi>Nobis alia eſt sententia quia ſciamus et in Germania,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Andr. Alci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atus de du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ello, c. <hi>32.</hi> Refer. Pet. Greg. in reg jur. H. <hi>6.</hi> capire <hi>10.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>et Gallia ſolum Barones dici quibus ſuper opidorum juriſdictionem haec dignitas ſpecialiter conceſſa eſt.</hi> Some thinke they are thoſe which are meant under the name of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alvaſores majores &amp; Capitanei.</hi> In the ſecond booke <hi>De feodis de titulo Quis dicatur dux, &amp;c.</hi> And ſome others would have the dignitie of a Baron to containe every noble dignitie un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Earle.<note place="margin">Grand de ſupplenda neglig. pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor. in Sex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to.</note> Some common Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers there are which extoll the digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:57614:22"/>of a Baron before that of the Earles, by reaſon of a ſubcription to a decretall epiſtle directed <hi>Baronibus &amp; Comit. regin Portugal.</hi> They not conſidering that in another place in the ſame decretals it is more orderlie pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, <hi>Nullus Imperator ſeu Rex Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus aut alius Imper. aut Rex, princeps Marchio, Dux, Comes aut Baro, &amp;c.</hi> Other ſome do equal the Baron with the Earle,<note place="margin">Baro. de Tan. Berg. refer. Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard. in Leuxiris.</note> affirming that <hi>Comiti Baro. prorſus equiparatur,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>nulla<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia niſi quod de Comitat. non ſit inveſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titus, &amp;c. haud quicquam Comite cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeatur inferior.</hi> And thus every one of them have written conformably to the cuſtomes of his particular Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey.</p>
               <p>But in this our Common-wealth of <hi>England</hi> (me thinkes) a Baron may be deſcribed in a generality anſwerable to every of the ſpeciall kinds thereof in this maner.<note place="margin">A Baron deſcribed.</note> A Barony is a dignitie of Nobilitie and honour next vnder the Viſcount, and above the Banaret and Vavaſour with the title of Lordſhip holding the ſame place with vs as did the <hi>Patritij</hi> or Senatour under the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:57614:22"/>Romanes. For the better vnderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whereof conſider that <hi>Nobilitas</hi> generally ſignifieth matter of note, but ſpecially it is applyed to expreſſe the reward of vertue in honourable mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures. <hi>Sc. generis claritatem</hi> of which there are two kinds <hi>Nobilitas major</hi> (viz) a Lord at leaſt, &amp; <hi>Nobilitas minor:</hi> but our engliſh tongue expreſſeth the higher kinde. A Barony therefore is a dignity of nobility and honour. A dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of Nobilitie to exclude all other kinds of dignities, of honour, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the leſſer kind of Nobilitie wherein Gentlemen are compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended. Dignities of Nobilities are with vs of two kinds <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> ſome are dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities of Nobilitie, honour, parcell of the name of thoſe that are innobled thereby, ſo that in publicke pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of law it is parcell of their name, and may not more be omitted then their ſurname, ſuch are the Nobilitie of Dukes, Earles, Vicounts. Others are Dignities onely,and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> not parcell of the name, and ſo is the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron, and therefore if an Action bee brought by or againſt a Baron, who
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:57614:23"/>hath but a Barony onely, it is not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite to make him Baron, which in all other Dignities being parcell of the name is otherwiſe moſt curiouſly obſerved,<note place="margin">8. <hi>H.</hi> 6.10. 32. <hi>H.</hi> 6.30 <hi>Littlet.</hi>
                  </note> otherwiſe the Writ ſhall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate; Thus much of the Dignitie of a Baron, now of the Etimologie of the Name.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>2.</hi> The Etimologie of the name Baron.</head>
               <p>MAny Writs have laboured to yeeld the Etimologie of the name wherein following their owne fancy there hath beene bred much va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietie of opinion, ſome men inducing the Greeke, importing Gravity, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers have ſought a Latine Author to father it upon,<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> alledging <hi>Cicero ad At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticum,</hi> where they find printed in ſome Copies theſe words, <hi>Apud Patronem &amp; reliquos Barones te in maximam gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> poſitum,</hi> where in other Copies in lieu thereof is read <hi>Barrones,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Alciat. lib. <hi>5.</hi> cap. <hi>16.</hi> &amp; <hi>32.</hi>
                  </note> and ſo by others the ſame is acknowledged to be nothing but a corruption whereof
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:57614:23"/>
                  <hi>Alciatus</hi> ſpeaketh, &amp;c. And therfore <hi>Raſius</hi> calleth the word <hi>Vanaſors &amp; vaſſallos,</hi> among the which they inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Barons to be included,<note place="margin">Sim. Shal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus in lexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co juris, Ptol. lib <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>6.</hi> Io Brekins de conſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tud. gallo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</note> 
                  <hi>Vocabula illota.</hi> Others would derive the word from a certaine war-like auncient people inhabiting ſome parts of <hi>Spaine,</hi> called <hi>Barones;</hi> or as <hi>Strabo</hi> and <hi>Ptolomy</hi> doe name them <hi>Barones,</hi> whoſe habitation was ſcituate vpon the Weſt-ſide of the River <hi>Euberus,</hi> who guarded the perſons of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Governours, as the Switzers are now vſed for the guarde of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Princes. Others derive the name from the manner of building of thoſe houſes that were given to Barons to be holden and were the head of their Baronies,<note place="margin">Petr. Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor. Syntax. lib. <hi>6.</hi> c. <hi>10.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Quod erant ejuſmodi domus undi<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> occluſae &amp; ſubſtructis turribus &amp; barris.</hi> Some thinke it to be an He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew name ſignifying mercenary ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, ſome would fetch it meerely from the Latine, <hi>Barones tanquam pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res homines;</hi> But the moſt probable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rivation is drawne from the Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therne peoples language, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaded the Romane Empire, among
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:57614:24"/>whom a Baron ſignified a man of ſtrength, as by the lawes of the Lom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bards, and as by the words yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining without much variation in every one of the ſaid three tongues, The word <hi>Varon</hi> and <hi>Baron,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tit. <hi>8</hi> in al. lib. tit. <hi>9.</hi> Tit. <hi>60.54.</hi>
                  </note> is vſed in ſtead of the Latine word <hi>Vir,</hi> and with this agreeth parcell of the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient law of <hi>Canutus, Quod eſt ſumma cenſus diverſarum dignitatum ſi mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noris Vironis, id eſt, Baronis duae librae: ſi majoris</hi> 4. &amp;c. And therfore in the Lombards lawes, compiled by <hi>K. Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tharis</hi> the word Baron is thus vſed <hi>ſi quis ex Baronibus noſtris ad nos vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luerit venire, ſecurus veniat &amp; illaeſus ad ſuos revertatur.</hi> And in thoſe old lawes called, <hi>Repnaria ſi quis homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem regni tabularium tam Barone qui foeminam abſtulerit,</hi> &amp;c. Where the word doth ſignifie the ſame that the word <hi>Vir</hi> doth in Latine;<note place="margin">Vir leges ſalvos: Bracton. lib. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> Therefore <hi>Bracton</hi> not vnfitly vſeth it <hi>ſunt &amp; alij potentes ſub rege qui dicuntur Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rones (hoc eſt) robur belli.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:57614:24"/>
               <head>The Antiquitie of the dignitie of Barons and the ſundry uſes of the name.</head>
               <p>IT ſeemeth that the dignitie was more auncient then the name for in the auncient conſtitution feudall of the <hi>Lombards,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lib <hi>2</hi> feud. titulo. <hi>10.</hi> lib feud. <hi>1.16.</hi> lib. <hi>1.</hi> feud <hi>1.7.</hi>
                  </note> there is not mention made of the name of Baron, howbeit the learned Interpreters underſtand that dignitie to be comprehended un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Valvaſores minores,</hi> or <hi>Valvaſini,</hi> or <hi>Valvaſores minimi,</hi> being another kind inferiour to <hi>Valv. majores,</hi> which were alſo called <hi>Capitanei (Barons.)</hi> The like Dignitie before the Conqueſt,<note place="margin">Lamb. de regimine Saxonum, fol. <hi>71.</hi>
                  </note> of whom is mention made in the Lawes of K. <hi>Ethelſton,</hi> and of this there were two kinds <hi>Thani Regis &amp; Thani alio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lamb. de regimine Saxon. fol. <hi>71.</hi>
                  </note> and therefore in the Records of Doomeſday in the deſeription of <hi>Hert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fordſh.</hi> and therein of the Mannor of <hi>Brackins</hi> it is thus written;<note place="margin">Record of Doomes-day Hert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fordſhire.</note> 
                  <hi>Hoc ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner' tenuel</hi> 2. <hi>taggas horum unus homo regis Edw. &amp; alter Aſgari ſteleri.</hi> This word <hi>Thani</hi> was diverſly uſed by the antient Saxons; Sometimes they ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:57614:25"/>thereby a Noble man, as by the Baron, ſometimes a freeman, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times a Magiſtrate, ſometimes a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant attendant upon a mans perſon, which they ſignified by the ſubſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the antient regall Charters by the word Miniſter, as <hi>Ego miniſter A. B. praeſens auſcultavi or interfui, or in inſpexi</hi> of the Kings <hi>Thanis.</hi> I find thus much written in the ſame Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords, <hi>Thanis vel Miles Regius domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicus moriens pro relevamento dimitte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat regi omnia arma ſua, &amp; equum unum cum Cella, &amp; alterum ſine cella. quod ſi eſſent ei canes vel accipitres pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentabunt regi ut ſi vellet acciperet.</hi> That the like was done alſo by the Thanis of others, as of Noblemen, Earles, and others, appeareth by an antient <hi>Saxon</hi> Teſtament of one <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frie</hi> an Earle, which is brought to light by Maſter <hi>Lambert,</hi> in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of <hi>Mephem</hi> in the preambu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of <hi>Kent</hi> in thoſe times. The <hi>Thanis</hi> were for the moſt part deemed Noble, and held one and the ſame dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, as the Barons doe. The word <hi>Thanis</hi> being uſuall in that ſence, not
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:57614:25"/>onely among our Engliſh <hi>Saxons,</hi> but alſo with the <hi>Scots</hi> and <hi>Danes,</hi> as concerning the Scots <hi>Hector</hi> Poet writeth, <hi>Malcolmum regem titulo Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitatum honeſtaſſe,</hi> And as touching the <hi>Dane;</hi> the <hi>Thanis</hi> among them are yet in uſe, as <hi>liberi Domini,</hi> ſuch as are the Barons, by this it may appeare, that the name of Baron was not uſuall amongſt the ancient Engliſh Saxons, for that in the ſubſcription unto the graunts of Kings, whereunto with the ſigne of the X were ſubſcribed the names of all noble perſonages, as well temporall as ſpirituall, the ſaid word Baron cannot bee heard of, but in an antient Charter made in the name of <hi>Zolpher,</hi> ſometimes King of <hi>Mercia,</hi> unto the Church of <hi>Peter-borough,</hi> having theſe words; <hi>Praeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pimus quod praedict. Monaſt. &amp; dona ſua ſint habenda,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ab omni diminuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one &amp; exact. comitum, &amp;c.</hi> Likewiſe to this effect have I ſeene in an old booke belonging to the Monaſt. of <hi>Weſt. Edg. Rex concilio habito infra ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilicum Weſtm. preſidente eo cum filio ſuo Edw. &amp; Dunſtano Archiepiſcopo, &amp;
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:57614:26"/>univerſis Epiſc &amp; Baronibus ſuis dicta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Eccleſia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de Westm. renovavit.</hi> Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, the name of Baron was not much vſed within the Realme untill the Norman Conqueſt, after which it grew very frequent. In which time the notable caſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of the Realme were debated before him and his Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons, and by them adjudged as by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Monuments extant may appeare,<note place="margin">Doomes-day in <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury.</hi>
                  </note> whereof one is in this manner in the Record of Doomes-day,<note place="margin">21. <hi>E.</hi> 3.6.</note> 
                  <hi>Quidam Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſit Brumanus eo tempore R. Edw. coepit conſuet. de extraneis mercatoribus, &amp;c.</hi> Alſo 21. <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. doth ſet forth by exemplification an act of Parliament made in a cauſe between the Abbot of Saint <hi>Edmondsbury,</hi> and <hi>Arfaſt</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times Biſhop of <hi>Thetford,</hi> which See was afterwards tranſlated by <hi>Herbert</hi> to <hi>Norwich</hi> concerning the Viſitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſaid Monaſterie, which Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament was holden by the ſaid King, the Archbiſhop of <hi>Cant,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Barkſhire.</note> and all other the Biſhops, Earles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> appeareth. Moreover in the Record of Doomes-day, in the deſcription of <hi>Doneſh</hi> is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, that at the time of the ſaid
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:57614:26"/>Record there were at <hi>Warham</hi> of certaine Barons lands twenty houſes ſtanding and ſeventy deſtroyed, by which appeareth that both name and dignitie of a Baron was ſufficiently knowne in the time of the Conqueſt, and as touching the vſe of the name the word Baron ſeemeth to be frequented among the <hi>Norman</hi> Conqu. of this Realme. In lieu of the word <hi>Thane</hi> among the <hi>Saxons,</hi> for as they in a large ſignification did ſometime uſe the ſame to the ſence, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of a free man borne of free parentage, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and ſo did the Normans vſe it, and therefore called their free Citizens of their beſt eſteemed Cities and Burgeſſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by the name of Barons,<note place="margin">Bracton <hi>272.</hi>
                  </note> and therfore the Citizens of <hi>London</hi> were called Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons <hi>Lond.</hi> in divers auntient Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents, of whom alſo <hi>Bracton</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, <hi>Per Barones Lond.</hi> &amp;c. So alſo there are diverſe Charters wherin mention is made of ſuch like Barons as the Barons of <hi>Warw.</hi> in Doomſ-day, and in our time the Burgeſſes of the five ports are called Barons, and divers of the Nobility of Barons as well ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:57614:27"/>as temporall, did in antient time ſet in the Exchequer in judicature. Moreover as our <hi>Saxons</hi> had two kinds of <hi>Thanis;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Fleta, lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 24. the judges of that Court have been from anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent times, and yet are called Barons of the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer.</note> the like hath been obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of Barons among the Norman Conqu. for the Kings of this Realme have had their immediate Barons be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Peeres of this Realme: ſo cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine other Noblemen, eſpecially the Earle <hi>Palatine</hi> and Earle Marchers, whoſe Counties have confined upon the coaſts of the enemie, have had under them a kind of Barons, as name<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly under the County <hi>Palatine</hi> of <hi>Cheſter</hi> were theſe Barons, the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons of <hi>Hatton, Monbatte, Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banke, Shipbrooke, Malpas, Maſy, Kingderſton, Stockport, &amp;c.</hi> The Earle-dome of <hi>Pembrooke,</hi> being firſt ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by <hi>Arnulphus Mountgomery,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">7 <hi>H.</hi> 6.35. 17. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter placita.</hi> 18. <hi>E.</hi> 2. <hi>Aſſiſ.</hi> 30. <hi>Camois.</hi>
                  </note> that conquered ſome part of the County, and therefore the Earle there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of being an Earle <hi>Marcher</hi> had alſo under him his Barons, for it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth by the Parliament rolles 18. <hi>E.</hi> 3. that the Baronies of <hi>Haverford, Cammois, Rochie,</hi> and <hi>Caſtlegoton,</hi> were antiently belonging to the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:57614:27"/>Iuriſdiction of the Earledome of <hi>Pem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brooke,</hi> and had their Chancery and Scals as other Barons upon the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches vſed to have. Hereof alſo it followed not onely in this Realme, but alſo elſe-where, that Earles had under them ſuch as they called their Barons, who held under them lands in Knights ſervice and in the defence of their Lords, and therefore in the Regiſter of the Monaſt, of Saint <hi>Iames</hi> of <hi>Northampton,</hi> it is found that <hi>Simon</hi> Ea. of <hi>Northampton,</hi> did get and confirme unto the ſaid <hi>Abbey, Omnia dona, &amp;c. quae Barones ſui, &amp;c. infra burgum &amp; extra North. illis dederunt.</hi> Many old Charters alſo are extant, whereby it appeares which now time hath worne out of memory, and yet the knowledge thereof ſerveth to good purpoſe, namely to reconcile the different opinion of ſome men con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the law,<note place="margin">20. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>Aſſ.</hi> 122.</note> for 20. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>Thorpe</hi> holdeth opinion that none can hold <hi>per Baron.</hi> but of the King onely, and that no ſubiect can aliene his land to another to hold of ſuch <hi>alienor per Baroniam,</hi> which ſome Serjeants
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:57614:28"/>denyed, to the which opinion of Serje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants <hi>Wilby</hi> and other judges agreed,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>2.</hi> E. <hi>3.</hi> Aſſ. <hi>124.</hi> Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rog. cap <hi>7.</hi>
                  </note> Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding further, that before the ſtatute of <hi>Prerog. Regis,</hi> thoſe that held <hi>per Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niam</hi> might aliene ſome parcell thereof to bee holden by other, ſince which is evident (ſaith he) in this that the antient Baronies doe conſiſt moſt of ſervices which began by occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſuch ſuites as aforeſaid. The aſſertion of both the ſaid Iudges is good law, for none can hold <hi>per Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roniam</hi> but of the <hi>K. Qu. &amp;c.</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchs of the Realme, And againe it is true that in ſome kind of feme a man may hold <hi>per Baron.</hi> of a ſubject but <hi>diverſis reſpect. ergo, diſtinguendu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt.</hi> None can hold <hi>per Baroniam</hi> as a Peere of the Realme, and in courſe of perfect Nobilitie but of the Crowne onely. For of this Bar. <hi>Bracton</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandeth when he ſaith it is the ſtrength of the Realme, and theſe Barons according to the law <hi>Senderl,</hi> are theſe, <hi>Capitanei or Valvaſor. Majo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res</hi> there ſpoken of: for <hi>Qui a principe vel ab aliqua poteſtate de plebe aliquare per feudum &amp; veſtitus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lib <hi>2.</hi> feu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall. tit. <hi>10</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>is Capitane us
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:57614:28"/>appellatur qui proprie Valvaſor. majores olim appellabantur,</hi> and of the queſtion ariſing concerning theſe Baronies, the Monarch of the Realme or the Iudges, for that thoſe Barons are immediate <hi>à Rege in feudali,</hi> as for others they be Barons <hi>ex ſimilitudine,</hi> and therfore thoſe which in the ſaid lawes feudall are called <hi>Valvaſores &amp; Valvaſini,</hi> for the words are theſe,<note place="margin">Bract. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Qui vero a Capitaneis antiquitus beneficium tenent Valvaſores ſunt, Qui autem a valvaſorib s feudum quod a Capitaneis habebatur, ſimiliter acceperint Valvaſini, id eſt, valicas minores appellantur,</hi> The vſe of this diviſion within <hi>England,</hi> hath beene in no other manner then this, The <hi>Valv. majores</hi> may be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood to be our Barons and Peeres for in ſuch manner the Interpreters of the law feudall have expreſſed the ſame. The ſecond ſort is the <hi>Valv. proprie</hi> of which degree <hi>Bracton</hi> alſo ſpeaketh: <hi>ſunt &amp; alij qui dicuntur Valvaſores magni dignitat. Valvaſor melus dici poterit quia vas ſortitum ad valetudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem.</hi> Howbeit the Civilians doe give another Etimologie in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:57614:29"/>
                  <hi>Valvaſor. quaſi ad valvas ſtantes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Shand Lexico in verb va<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ve Pet. Greg. lib. <hi>6.</hi> ca. <hi>11.13</hi> E. <hi>3.</hi> Chal <hi>115.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>id eſt, tanquam ad valvas tentorij dum ſunt in bello excubantes ad quamlibet injuriam propulſandam;</hi> And of theſe <hi>valvaſi,</hi> which are properly the <hi>Val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſi</hi> indeed, mention is made 13. <hi>E.</hi> 3. For they may be impannelled in a Iury among the Kinghts where a Baron is party. The third ſort called <hi>Valvaſini</hi> inſpecial name we have not in vſe, Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſſe they are in nature the ſame that we call Lords and proprietors of Mannors, who alſo in reſpect of their Tenants were oftentimes in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient remembrances called Barons, but <hi>(abuſive)</hi> and their Courts, Court-Barons, for of theſe <hi>Glanvill</hi> ſpeaketh,<note place="margin">Glan lib. <hi>8.</hi> cap. <hi>10.</hi> fol <hi>64.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Praeterea Record. habeant minores Cur. de his quae in eis facta ſunt, &amp;c.</hi> hence it is that theſe divers degrees have beene obſerved in forraigne Countries; By the French Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it is ordained, that <hi>Si quis aut Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>com. aut Baro voluerit fieri comes, neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſariu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ducu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t eum habere in ſua ditione.</hi> 4. <hi>Baronias &amp; tres caſtella. quaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libet habeat ſaltem</hi> 10.<note place="margin">Pet. Ger. in lib. <hi>6.</hi> cap <hi>9.</hi> Ex edito regis gall. <hi>17.</hi> Angl. <hi>1579</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Nobiles ſibi ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit os qui eum comitari poſſunt.</hi> Again, in
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:57614:29"/>
                  <hi>tit. comit. nullus tranſeat niſi ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beat</hi> 2. <hi>Baroneas, &amp;</hi> 3. <hi>Caſtellaneas aut ſaltem, i. Baroniam &amp;</hi> 6. <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtellaneas vnitas &amp; nomine feudi Poſſeſſat &amp; inveſtitas a rege ſub uno titulo.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jac Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant. Fland. <hi>16.</hi> cap <hi>1</hi> de Aloſto.</note> In <hi>Flanders</hi> which was an Earl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of regall conſtitution there was in auntient time an Earledome the Ea. whereof was intituled <hi>Comes Aleſtanus</hi> the Earle of <hi>Elſton,</hi> who although his juriſdiction was parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular to himſelfe from the Emperour, yet had he under him five Barons, the memory of which doth remaine; It hath beene heretofore a common re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived opinion, that every Earldome in times paſT had under it ten Barons, and every Baron ſeven Knights fees holden of him, and ſome are of opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that thoſe which had foureteene Knights fees were uſually Barons, but of that more hereafter.</p>
               <p>It reſteth now for the more expla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the uſe of the name <hi>Baron,</hi> that wee call to remembrance that which is before ſpoken, that the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of our Countrey is, that if a Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron be created an Earle; the eldeſt ſon
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:57614:30"/>of the ſaid Earle, in the life of his l'a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, taketh upon him the title of the Barony, although he want the privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges belonging to a Baron. Laſtly, that is not to be omitted, that by the generall name of the Barons of the Realme, wee doe underſtand the whole body of the Nobility, and hence it is that the civill warre concerning the liberties granted in the great Charter, both in the time of King <hi>Iohn,</hi> and <hi>H.</hi> 3. proſecuted by the whole Nobilitie ſome few excepted, are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Barons warres; Thus much of their antiquitie, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Having before ſhewed the ſeverall uſes of the word <hi>Baron,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The true uſe of the name.</note> we are now to adhere onely to the proper ſignificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof, whereby there is denoted to us an Honourable perſonage next under the Vicount, and therefore wee are to ſet forth a diviſion.</p>
               <p>Barons honourable are of three kindes,<note place="margin">3. kinds of Barons.</note> by Tenure, by Writ, by Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Patent, as for the Baron by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription they are all one with the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:57614:30"/>Barons by tenure, or thoſe who anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently, and time out of mind have been called to the Parliament by Writ, and otherwiſe none.</p>
               <p>Barons by tenure are thoſe which doe any honour,<note place="margin">Barons by tenure 2. kinds.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as the head of their Barony, <hi>per Baroniam,</hi> which is called <hi>Graund Serjeanty;</hi> Theſe are of two ſorts ſpirituall and temporall.</p>
               <p>The Barons ſpirituall <hi>per Tenure,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Spirituall.</note> are and were thoſe Eccleſiaſticall perſons, which held the principall part of their ſpirituall living <hi>per Baron.</hi> and ſuch were alſo of two kinds; firſt, the Archbiſhops and Biſhops of this Realme, who doe hold the principall part of their temporalties <hi>per Baron.</hi> Secondly, ſuch Abbots, Priors, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which were extinguiſhed by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to the Crowne by the Statute.</p>
               <p>Barons temporall are ſuch as hold the chiefeſt part of their poſſeſſions,<note place="margin">Temporal.</note> as ſome honour, Caſtle, <hi>&amp;c. per Bar.</hi> of the Crowne, all which honourable Barons of holding their Baronies of the Crown were in antient time in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of theſe their tenures called by the Monarch of this Realme to aſſiſt him
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:57614:31"/>in counſell in Parliament.</p>
               <p>But firſt it ſhall be requiſite to prove every part of the diviſion, namely of Barons by tenure, and firſt of ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall.</p>
               <p>It is evident, that the Archbiſhops and Biſhops of the Realme in the Saxon dayes, as well during the time that it was divided into divers king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, as alſo after the uniting of them into one Monarchy were called to the Parliament, not ſo much in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of their tenure (for it was then by <hi>Frankalmoigne</hi>) but eſpecially for that lawes are then moſt commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable, when they are grounded upon the law of God,<note place="margin">Hiſt. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guelf. Ab. de Croland. in ſubſcrip. Chartre Bertofli re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis, fol. <hi>490</hi> ibid. <hi>492.</hi>
                  </note> and therefore our wiſe Anceſtours called to their gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Counſell or <hi>Wittenaymot</hi> or Court of wiſe men, as they called it thoſe principall perſons of their Clergie, which by their profeſſion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> might adviſe them to frame their lives an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerably, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nevertheleſſe, ſhortly after the Norman Conqueſt, the Conquerour altered tenures, being before <hi>Frank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alm.</hi> not without ſome complaint
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:57614:31"/>and griefe of the Clergie of which <hi>Matth. Paris</hi> thus writeth <hi>An.</hi> 1070. which prove that Biſhops then held <hi>per Baroniam.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matt. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, fol <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>In the Conſtitution held at <hi>Clarin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don tempore, H.</hi> 2. <hi>Anno</hi> 1164. which conſtitutions certaine recapitulations of the prerogative of the King and his people then ſought to be infringed by the Pope and his Clergie,<note place="margin">Called the Aſſiſ. of <hi>Clarindo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </hi> in old Writers.</note> it is thus expreſſed in the 11. Article, <hi>Archie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopi &amp; Epiſcopi, &amp; univerſa perſona regni qui de rege ten' in Cap. habeat poſſeſſion. ſuas de Rege ſicut Baroniam, &amp; inde reſpondeant Juſticiarijs,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Regis &amp; faciant omnes conſuet. regias, &amp; ſicut caeteri Barones debeant intereſſe judicijs curiae Regis cum Baronibus quouſque. perveniatur ad diminutionem membro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum vel mortem.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>10.</hi> E. <hi>4.6.</hi> De Rot. Parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. <hi>11.</hi> R. <hi>2.</hi> an no <hi>9</hi> in turr. Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</note> Here we ſee the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Biſhops in the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in reſpect of their Baronies, <hi>Quouſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> perveniatur ad diminutionem, &amp;c.</hi> For ever unto our times when queſtion is had of any attainder of any Peere in Parliament, they depart the higher houſe, and make their procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rators, for by the Decrees of the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:57614:32"/>Church, they may not be judges of life and death.</p>
               <p>Of the Baronies of Biſhops,<note place="margin">Lib <hi>9.</hi> fol. <hi>66.</hi>
                  </note> and of their homage for the ſame; Thus wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth <hi>Glanvill,</hi> who <hi>tempore R.</hi> 1. was chiefe Juſtice, <hi>Epiſcopi vero conſecrati homagium facere non ſolent Domino regi etiam de Baronijs ſuis ſed fidelitat. cum jurament. interpoſit. ipſi praeſtare ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent; Elect. vero in epiſcopos ante conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craetione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuam homag. ſua facere ſolent.</hi> Of theſe alſo <hi>Bracton</hi> ſaith, <hi>St autem terra data fuit Eccleſiat. Cathedral. vel conventurae non jacebit aſſiſa utrum quamvis in habitam,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Eleemoſinam.</hi> Of the which hee reciteth a Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>P.</hi> 15. <hi>H.</hi> 3. which was given in a Writ of Errour upon a Judgement in Eire betweene the Prior of <hi>Lewes &amp; Gilb. de Aquila,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bract lib <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>2.287.</hi>
                  </note> and he yeeldeth the reaſon thereof.</p>
               <p>Againe,<note place="margin">Bract. lib. <hi>5.</hi> cap. <hi>23.</hi> fol. <hi>4.27.</hi>
                  </note> he in another place, ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out the reaſon why the certificate <hi>Excommunicat. ſpiritualium,</hi> any ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Judge other then the Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Biſhops of this Realme is not by any Law to be admitted, hee yeeldeth this reaſon ſo, that none of
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:57614:32"/>thoſe other ſpirituall Judges are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellable to admit the action as are the the Archbiſhops and Biſhops, <hi>Quia rex in epiſcopis coercionem habet propter Baroniam,</hi> Meaning thereby that upon their contempt the King doth ſeaze their temporaltie. Likewiſe, about 46. <hi>E.</hi> 3. the Biſhop of <hi>Chicheſter</hi> Leaſed for life a Mannor parcell of his B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny with licence of the King,<note place="margin">46. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>forf.</hi> 8.</note> this alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation was a forfeiture becauſe parcell of his Barony.</p>
               <p>Many more authorities might be cited out of Records and bookes of Law,<note place="margin">13. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>Chal.</hi> 115. <hi>enqueſt.</hi> 43.29. <hi>E.</hi> 3.42.</note> in regard whereof they have in antient time been named Peeres of the Realme, and have enjoyed other the priviledges that Peeres doe the triall by Peeres (onely in matters of Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or miſpriſion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> excepted) wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of <hi>Stamford</hi> giveth the reaſon, <hi>Non ratione Nobilitatis ſed ratione officij.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">39. <hi>E.</hi> 3.30. 31. <hi>E.</hi> 3.94. 21. <hi>E.</hi> 4 77 27. <hi>H.</hi> 8. 27. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nquſt.</hi> 99. 2. <hi>Mar.</hi> 46. 35. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>Triall.</hi> 142. <hi>Stan.</hi> 1536. 1. <hi>H.</hi> 4.13. <hi>H</hi> 8 11.</note> Another reaſon why Biſhops are not tryed by Peeres as other Peeres, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they cannot paſſe upon the life of any man, being thereunto forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den by <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and therefore the Peeres cannot trie them, for that this kind of
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:57614:33"/>triall ſhould be mutuall if the offence give occaſion, inſomuch that their cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure is upon their honour without oath, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The like of thoſe Abbotts,<note place="margin">21. <hi>E.</hi> 3.88 36. <hi>H.</hi> 6. 7. <hi>H.</hi> 6.108. 7. <hi>H.</hi> 4.2. 26. <hi>H.</hi> 8.7. 21. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>n.</hi> 50.</note> Priors, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which held ſome part of their land <hi>per Bar.</hi> who were alſo called Peeres of the Realme, therefore no Capias againſt them, and therfore ſome of them that held not <hi>per Bar.</hi> being ſummoned to the Parliament upon their petition were diſcharged, whereof there are ſome preſidents extant.</p>
               <p>The Abbot of Saint <hi>Iames</hi> neere <hi>North<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mpton,</hi> in 12. <hi>E.</hi> 3. was ſummo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the Parliament, which was the ſame yeere holden at <hi>Yorke,</hi> who becauſe neither he nor his predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors were ſummoned, and becauſe he held onely by <hi>Frankalm.</hi> hee by his Procurator exhibited his petition to the Lord Chancellour a monument wherof I have ſeen in this ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner, <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas Sancti Iacobi North, Irrotul. de novo in Cancell. dom. Regis inter citand. ad Parliamentum &amp; non tent per Baroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am nec de rege in Capite ſed tantum in
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:57614:33"/>pura,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Out of the Regiſter booke of St. <hi>Iames</hi> of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thampton.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>&amp;c. Eleemoſina &amp; nec ipe nec pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſor. ſui unquam in Cancellaria ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rotulat. fuerunt nec ad Parliamentum cita. huc vſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> unde idem Abbas petit remedium. Ad cujus billam execut. Dominus Cancellar. cum ſuo Conſilio de Cancell. ordinavit quod nomen praedict. Abbatis a regiſtro Cancel. deleretur &amp; ita pluribus circumſpect. idem Abbas eſt abſolutus; facta eſt haec excuſatio per vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum Domini Iohannis de Oth. Epiſcopi Elien. Cancil. domini regis, domini Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lielmi Dirmins tunc cust. rotulorum &amp; al'.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A like Petition was made by the Abbot of <hi>Leiceſter</hi> unto <hi>K.E.</hi> 3. and thereupon obtained a Writ of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge in this forme;<note place="margin">Ex. rot. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent. <hi>26.</hi> E. <hi>3.</hi> pars. <hi>1.</hi> M. <hi>22.</hi> in turri Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</note> 
                  <hi>Edwardus Dei gratia</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Salut. ſupplicavit nobis di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect. nobis in Chriſto Abbas de Leyceſt. in Abbatia ſua predict per Robert. Fits, Roberti de Mellent dudum Com. Leyc. fundata fuiſſet in pura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eleemoſinam, &amp; advocat.ſibi preornat. ad manus Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni Hen. quondam regiae Angl. proavi nostri per forisfacturam, Simon. de Monte forte tunc Com. Leyc. &amp; proin ejuſdem darent, idem<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Abbas alij<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>
                     <pb n="62" facs="tcp:57614:34"/>terras ſive tenta de nobis per Baron. ſive ali<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> modo non tenuit per quod ad Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum venire<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> teneatur, nec aliquis predeceſſorum ſuorum ante</hi> 49 <hi>annum Domini proavi noſtri part. forisfactu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram dicti Simonis quo anno omnes Abbat. &amp; Priores regni noſtri ad par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liamentum, proavi noſtri tunc tenturum &amp; voluntarie ſummoniti fuerunt ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monit. extiterit velimus ipſum Abbat. de hujuſmodi adventu ad Parliamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum facere exonerari, &amp; quia viſis chartis &amp; confirm. de terris, &amp; tentis eidem Abbati dat. &amp; conceſſis in Rot. Cancell. noſtri irrotulat. compertum eſt quod dicta Abbat. praedict. Rober<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti Fitzs Robert Com. Leyc. fundat. erat in pura elemoſina, &amp; non invenimus quod praedict. Abbaes aliquas terras de nobis tenuit. per Baron. &amp;c. nec quod predeceſſor. ſui adalia parliamenta pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genitorum noſtrorum ante praedict.</hi> 49. <hi>Annum dicti proavi noſtri, aut poſt modum continue, ſed vicibus interpellatis ſummonit. fuerint nolentes ipſum Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat. indebite ſic vexari Conceſſimus pro nobis, &amp;c. quod idem Abbas. &amp;c. de ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niendo ad Parliamentum, &amp;c. quieti
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:57614:34"/>ſint; Ita ſemper quod dictus Abbas, &amp;c. in procurator. ad hujuſmodi parliamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta per clerum mittenda conſentient, &amp; ut moris eſt expenſis contribuant corun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam In cujus rei Teſt. &amp;c.</hi> 15. <hi>Febr. Anno</hi> 26. <hi>&amp; Franc.</hi> 13. <hi>per Petition. parliament.</hi> Whereby it appeareth, that Barons by tenure are ſummoned in reſpect of their tenure.</p>
               <p>As touching the temporall Barons by tenure mention is often made of them in the yeare-booke Records,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Glan.</hi> 9. <hi>c.</hi> 6</note> 
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as <hi>Glanv. lib.</hi> 9. <hi>cap.</hi> 6. <hi>Baroniam reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net rex donec haeres, &amp;c.</hi> Which reliefe for Baronies was at that time incer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, and rentable at the Kings plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, but ſuch incertainty of reliefe was brought to certaintie by the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of <hi>Magn. Chart. ſi quis,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mag Char. cap. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>&amp;c. de Comitat. integro per C.<hi rend="sup">1</hi>. haeres Baron. per C. mercas, haeres Mil. per feodo mil. C. ſolidos.</hi> Thus much of the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall Baron and his reliefe.</p>
               <p>In 3. <hi>H.</hi> 3. there was agnized an auntient perogative belonging to the Crowne and uſuall from the Conqu. in theſe words and ſo reported by <hi>Fitz-Herb. Quod ſi aliquis Baron. obijſſet,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:57614:35"/>&amp; non h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>beret haere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>em niſi filias &amp; primogenit. filia marit. ſit in vita patris Rex daret poſt natum filium quod re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maneret in haereditat patris,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bract lib. <hi>5</hi> Tract. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>2.</hi> fol. <hi>337.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>&amp;c. Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cton</hi> writing of eſſoignes delivereth this learning, that if any Baron that holdeth <hi>per Baroniam</hi> hath his abſence excuſed by eſſoigne, he which caſteth ſuch eſſoigne ought to find ſuretie that it is true, but in the caſe of common perſons that ſhall reſt upon credit, and the integritie of the Eſſoigner; His words be theſe, <hi>Ideo ne eſſoniator,</hi> &amp;c. by which appeareth that there are temporall Bar. by tenure.</p>
               <p>Now let us deſcend to the other au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities Sir <hi>Ralph Everdon</hi> Knight,<note place="margin">48. <hi>E.</hi> 3.30.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one of the Barons of the Realme <hi>tempore E</hi> 3. was impannelled in a Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to their priviledge, and therefore for his exemption procured a Writ di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to the Judges of <hi>C.B.</hi> before whom the Jury was impannelled, by which they were commanded to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge the ſaid Sir <hi>Ralph,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Reg.</hi> 179.14. <hi>&amp;.</hi> 15. <hi>H</hi> 8.35. <hi>H.</hi> 6.46.</note> whereupon <hi>Belke</hi> chiefe Juſtice of <hi>C.B.</hi> exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him whether he held <hi>per Baroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am</hi> or no, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and whether hee had
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:57614:35"/>come to the Parliament as a Baron, to which he anſwered that he held by a certaine part of a Baron. and that his Aunceſt. had likewiſe ſo done vpon good advice, by means whereof he was diſcharged, in which caſe is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved that there are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arons by tenure, and that they in regard of their tenure ought to be ſummoned.</p>
               <p>In the Parliament 23. <hi>H.</hi> 6. there was a controuerſie between <hi>W. E.</hi> of <hi>Arundell,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Inter. rot. Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, <hi>27.</hi> H. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> and <hi>Tho. E.</hi> of <hi>Devon.</hi> for their places in the Kings preſence as well in the Parliament, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon there were diuers writings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> declared betweene them in the ſaid Parliament; the conſideration whereof was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted by the King to certaine Lords of the Parliament to decide the ſaid title with all incidents thereto belonging. Nevertheleſſe it being not accordingly performed and the ſaid controverſie remaining vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decided in the next Parliament 27. <hi>H.</hi> 8. the ſaid K. was pleaſed that the Iudges ſhould examine the ſaid matter, who having conſidered the allegations of either part, and alſo an
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:57614:36"/>act of Parliament made 11. <hi>H.</hi> 6. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ſame in the behalfe of <hi>Iohn E.</hi> of <hi>Arundell</hi> decided; his Anceſtors they certified, firſt, that the contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie was never matter of Parliament 2. that the ſaid act wherby it was or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained that the ſaid <hi>Iohn</hi> ſhould have his ſeat in the Kings preſence a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> well in Parliament as elſ-where as <hi>E.</hi> of <hi>Arundell</hi> there was no mention made of his heires but of himſelfe. 3. That to the caſtle, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of <hi>Arundell</hi> the name, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of Earle then was, and time out of mind had beene vnited and annexed, and by reaſon thereof the ſaide <hi>E.</hi> did hold that name and not by creation, all which being ſo certified it was enacted that the ſaid <hi>W. E.</hi> of <hi>Arundell</hi> ſhould retaine his prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence by reaſon of the eaſtle as wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfully (for ſo are the words of the act) as any of the <hi>E.</hi> of <hi>Ar.</hi> above the <hi>E.</hi> of <hi>Devon, &amp;c.</hi> ſaving alwayes to the ſaid <hi>E.</hi> of <hi>Devon</hi> his lawfull ſuite to the King in his high court of Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament for his right, by which Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent we do plainly ſee that the digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of that Earled. was <hi>annexa feode,</hi>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:57614:36"/>and an Earldome by tenure, in regard of which the Earles thereof have had their place in Parliament, from whence may be deduced that the like may be obſerved of Baronies by tenure as of this <hi>E.</hi> by tenure I would wiſh thoſe that denye Baronies by tenure to conſider the ſtatute of <hi>Weſt.</hi> 2. <hi>cap</hi> 42. where the Fees of the <hi>E.</hi> Marſhall and Lord Chamberlaine are expreſſed, which are to be taken by them vpon the homage of euery Baron by tenure where he holdeth by a whole Barony or by leſſe, And leſt any ſhould thinke that this ordained by the Statute ſhould concerne any other Marſhall or Chamberlaine, <hi>Fleta</hi> will put him out of doubt,<note place="margin">Fleta. lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> which applyeth them to this purpoſe.</p>
               <p>But ere wee proceed further there a riſeth a Quere.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:57614:37"/>
               <head>If a Baron by tenure grant the hononr holden by Barony. whether ſhall ſuch grantee have the ſaid dignitie or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe?</head>
               <p>
                  <label>Argument ex parte neg.</label> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> THey which deny Baronies by te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nure doe vſe this as their princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall reaſon, firſt, if there be any, then the Grantee of them muſt hold by the ſame tenure as their Feoffer,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>10.2.</hi> ca <hi>1.</hi> Qu. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mp. terrar.</note> but that was <hi>per Baroniam:</hi> the refore. And if ſuch Grant bee made to perſons ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noble, they then ſhould bee Noble which were abſured.<note place="margin">Ratio <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, it is very evident that many antient Mannors, which in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient time were holden <hi>per Baron.</hi> are now in the tenures of meane Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, who may not dare to chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge it.</p>
               <p> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, ſome antient Barons are which have ſold thoſe Caſtles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and yet retaine their dignitie, and have been, and are ſummoned to Parliament notwithſtanding.<note place="margin">Diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable.</note>
               </p>
               <p>For the better anſer, it ſhall bee convenient to exhibit certaine neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:57614:37"/>diſtinctions and thence to draw in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible diſtinctions, and then Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Preſidents.</p>
               <p>Firſt therefore if a Baron by tenure doe aliene the ſame,<note place="margin">Diſtinct 1</note> either he doth it without licence, or elſe with licence obtained. If without Licence,<note place="margin">The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion.</note> then the Concluſion is certaine that it is forfeited, and to be ſeized to the King, and the Dignity extinguiſhed in the Crown from whence it was derived.</p>
               <p>The reaſon is out of <hi>Bracton,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Baronies are the ſtrength of the Kingdome, and if they ſhould be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liened without conſent of the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riagne, baſe perſons innobled without deſert, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for where the thing ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liened is an Honour, it differeth much from the ordinary tenure in Cap. whereof if the Tenant make alienati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on without licence,<note place="margin">50. <hi>E.</hi> 3 <hi>c.</hi> 10.</note> he is onely to make a fine by the Statute. For authoritie. <hi>Glanvill</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Mag. Char. cap <hi>31.</hi> Glanv. l. <hi>7.</hi> cap. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Notandum eſt quod nec Epiſcopus, nec Abbas quia corum Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niae ſunt de Eleemoſina Regis non poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunt de Dominicis ſuis aliquam partem dare ad remanenciam ſine aſſenſu, &amp; conſenſu Domini Regis.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:57614:38"/>
               <p>In 20. <hi>E.</hi> 3. certaine land being par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of the Baronie of <hi>Brenbur</hi> was aliened by <hi>W.de Bruce,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">20. <hi>Aſſ.</hi> 1 8 20 <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>Aſſ.</hi> 122. &amp; 224.</note> the Baron thereof without licence, and in the argument of a Caſe concerning the ſame, <hi>Greene</hi> ſaid that parcell of a Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronie, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> held in chiefe, cannot bee aliened without his Licence. Againe, 46. <hi>E.</hi> 3. it was found by Office, that <hi>W.</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Cheſter</hi> had Leaſed for life to <hi>Io. Peſton</hi> a Mannor,<note place="margin">46. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>Forf.</hi> 18.</note> parcell of the Baronie without Licence, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved that it was forfeited, but by mediation of the ſaid Counſell, the Biſhop ſubmitted and made a fine, and ſeverall <hi>Scire faec.</hi> iſſued againſt the perceptors of the profits to anſwer the King.<note place="margin">Diſtinct. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> Thus much of Alienation without Licence.</p>
               <p>But of the other part, if a Baron by tenure doth aliene by Licence wee muſt diſtinguiſh, for it is either made for the continuance of his Barony, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or elſe for ſome other conſideration.</p>
               <p>That if any ſuch Alienation be made for the continuance of the Barony in the name, then have the iſſue male with the Caſtle, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> retained the Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:57614:38"/>of a Baron, and hereof have the Heires generall, or next Heires fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>males beene excluded; And for proofe of this aſſertion many antient Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents may be produced, ſeeing they have happened almoſt in every age for three hundred yeares ſpace, of which ſome certaine doe enſue.</p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Barony of <hi>Grooby</hi> in <hi>Com. Ley<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſt.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <head>Willielm.dr Ferariis Co. Derbie obiit anno 38.H.3</head>
                     </figure>
                     <figure>
                        <head>Margaret Com. Derb &amp; Domina deGrooby</head>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <head>Robeitus de Ferariis Comes de Derbie.</head>
                     </figure>
                     <figure>
                        <head>VVil De Ferariis Dom De Grooby ex Do. Mris</head>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <head>Iohannes de Ferariis Dominus de Cartley</head>
                     </figure>
                     <figure>
                        <head>VVill. de Ferariis Do. Minus de Grooby</head>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <figDesc>family tree Barons of Grooby</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:57614:39"/>
               <p>It appeareth by an Office found af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the death of <hi>William, de Ferarijs,</hi> Lord of <hi>Grooby</hi> 23, <hi>H.</hi> 6. that <hi>Marga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret</hi> Lady of <hi>Grooby,</hi> gave to <hi>William Ferarijs</hi> her ſecond ſonne in taile the Mannor of <hi>Grooby,</hi> by vertue whereof hee and his Heires wee Barons of <hi>Grooby.</hi>
               </p>
               <figure>
                  <head>
                     <hi>The Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of</hi> Kel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cke Com Hereof.<note place="margin">Temp. E. <hi>1.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <head>VVillelm. Baro de Kelpecke.</head>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <head>Rob. VVallero Baro de Kel. obit ſi neprod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>. F.1</head>
                     </figure>
                     <figure>
                        <head>Alicca Nuptal Laynec.</head>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <head>VVilielmus VValleion.</head>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <head>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>anus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Laynet Baro de Kelp. ra io. Don.</head>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <head>Robertus VValleron Prox Hae-res.</head>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <figDesc>family tree</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>
                  <hi>Robertus Walleron,</hi> Baron of <hi>Kel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecke</hi> died, 1. <hi>E.</hi> 1. without heire of
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:57614:39"/>his body, and <hi>Robert</hi> Sonne of <hi>William,</hi> Brother of the ſaid <hi>Robert,</hi> was his next Heire, yet he gave to <hi>Allen Play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell</hi> the Lordſhip of <hi>Kelpecke,</hi> &amp;c. in taile, by force whereof he was Baron, and ſummoned to the Parliament, and he died <hi>Anno</hi> 27. <hi>E.</hi> 1.</p>
               <figure>
                  <head>
                     <hi>The Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of</hi> Plankenoy in Com. Lincolne.<note place="margin">Temp. E. <hi>2.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <head>Iohn Dreyn. court.</head>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <head>tam: D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>n court Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>on of Bla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>knoy obiit, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>o E.2</head>
                     </figure>
                     <figure>
                        <head>VV.Dreyne. ba. of Blank. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ntayled o-biit 38.E.3.</head>
                     </figure>
                     <figure>
                        <head>Iohn Dreyn-court.</head>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <head>Edmond Dreyncourt.</head>
                     </figure>
                     <figure>
                        <head>VVillielm. Dreyncourt obiit ante <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>atrem.</head>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <head>Iſabell his next heire.</head>
                     </figure>
                     <figure>
                        <head>VVilliam Dreyncourt baron. of Blanknoy</head>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <figDesc>family tree</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:57614:40"/>
               <p>The King to all,<note place="margin">Pat. Anno <hi>10</hi> E. <hi>2.</hi> part <hi>2.</hi> num. <hi>13.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi> greeting; Know yee, that whereas lately our welbeloved <hi>Edm. Dreincourt</hi> conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that both his ſirname, and alſo his Armes after his death in the perſon of <hi>Iſabel Dreincourt</hi> ſhould bee quite blotted out of memory, moſt earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſired, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> To whoſe requeſt in conſideration of ſervice to our Father and our ſelfe by our Letters Patents do grant ſo much as in us lyeth to the ſaid <hi>Edm.</hi> to diſpoſe to whom hee pleaſeth.</p>
               <p>By vertue whereof he gave them to <hi>William</hi> ſonne of <hi>John Dreincourt</hi> in taile,<note place="margin">Eſch. <hi>22.</hi> E. <hi>3.</hi> S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m. Parl. <hi>7.</hi> E. <hi>3.</hi> Clauſ. dors. part. <hi>25.</hi>
                  </note> the ſaid <hi>Edm.</hi> died <hi>ult. Ed</hi> 2. <hi>&amp; tempore E.</hi> 3. <hi>William</hi> was ſummoned to the Parliament by vertue of that gift till his death, which was <hi>Anno</hi> 38. <hi>E.</hi> 3.</p>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:57614:40"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>The Barony of Holgate Com. Salop.</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <head>Philip Barnell baron of Holgate</head>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <head>Edward Barnell baron of Holgate</head>
                     </figure>
                     <figure>
                        <head>Iohn Lovell <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>he firſt Husband.</head>
                     </figure>
                     <figure>
                        <head>Maude Barnell heire to her brother</head>
                     </figure>
                     <figure>
                        <head>Iohn Hand-lowe the ſcond huſ-band</head>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <head>Iohn Lord Lovell.</head>
                     </figure>
                     <figure>
                        <head>Nicholas Handlowe Baron of Holgate</head>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <head>Iohn Lord Lovell.</head>
                     </figure>
                     <figure>
                        <head>Hugh Handlowe alias Bunnell Baron of Holgate</head>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <head>Iocoſa Vxor Tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>nae Ed-dington</head>
                     </figure>
                     <figure>
                        <head>Margery uxor Ed-wardi Hungerford.</head>
                     </figure>
                     <figure>
                        <head>Paterina ux-or Iohannis Talbot.</head>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <figDesc>family tree</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:57614:41"/>
               <p>It appeareth by divers officers in the time of <hi>Ed.</hi> the third, that <hi>Iohn Handlowe</hi> in the right of <hi>Maude</hi> his wife, was ſeized of the Mannor of <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate. Acton Burnell, &amp;c.</hi> for life, the remainder to <hi>Nic. Handlowe (alias) Burnell,</hi> ſonne of the ſaid <hi>Maude</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> by a fine in Court, And that <hi>Iohn Lovell</hi> was next heire of the ſaid <hi>Maude</hi> and her firſt borne ſonne by her firſt Husband. And afterwards the ſaid <hi>Nicholas</hi> was ſummoned among the Barons of this Realme to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament by reaſon of the fine aforeſaid. And not the ſaid <hi>Iohn Lovell</hi> that was next heire.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thomas de Beauchampe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſch Anno <hi>43.</hi> Ed <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> the elder Earle of <hi>WarWicke,</hi> by a fine levyed 18. <hi>E.</hi> 3. intayled the Mannor and Caſtle of <hi>Warw.</hi> with divers other poſſeſſions to himſelfe for terme of his life, the Remainder thereof to <hi>Guy</hi> his eldeſt ſonne, and to the heires males of his body iſſuing, and for want of ſuch Heires, the Remainder to come to <hi>Tho. Beauchampe</hi> brother to the aforeſaid <hi>Guy,</hi> and to the Heires males of his body, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And after the ſaid
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:57614:41"/>
                  <hi>Guy</hi> died without Heires males of his body, leaving two Daughters and Heires living. Afterward the ſaid Earle died, and the ſaid <hi>Thom.</hi> the ſonne entered into the Caſtle, and Mannor aforeſaid with other the premiſſes and was E. of <hi>Warw.</hi> by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the intaile aforeſaid, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that <hi>Katherine</hi> Daughter of <hi>Guy</hi> next heire to the ſaid <hi>Tho.</hi> the elder was living thirty yeeres after his death.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Richard</hi> Earle of <hi>Arundell</hi> by a fine levied 21. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. intayled the Caſtle towne,<note place="margin">Eſch. Anno <hi>9.</hi> H. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of <hi>Arund.</hi> to him and the Heires males of the body of <hi>Elinor</hi> his wife, by vertue whereof <hi>Iohn Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travers</hi> was E. of <hi>Arun.</hi> after the death of <hi>Tho.</hi> the Earle, who died without iſſue male although his Siſters poſſeſſed divers lands where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he died ſeized in fee.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thomas</hi> the elder, Lord <hi>Barkeley,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſch. <hi>5.</hi> H. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> was ſeized in Fee of the Caſtle of <hi>Barkely</hi> and mannor, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And by a fine levied in 23. <hi>E.</hi> 3. he intayled the ſaid Caſtle, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to himſelfe for life, the Remainder to <hi>Maurice</hi> his ſonne in
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:57614:42"/>taile with other Remainder as before, which ſaid <hi>Maurice</hi> had iſſue <hi>Tho.</hi> Lord <hi>Barkley</hi> and Sir <hi>Iohn,</hi> which <hi>Iohn,</hi> died in the life of his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, leaving <hi>James</hi> his Sonne and heire living, after the ſaid <hi>Tho.</hi> died 5. <hi>H.</hi> 5. leaving <hi>Elizabeth</hi> his daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and heire married to <hi>Richard</hi> Earle of <hi>Warw.</hi> after whoſe death <hi>James</hi> the Nephew entered into the ſaid Caſtle,<note place="margin">Som Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament. <hi>9</hi> H. <hi>5.</hi> Eſch. <hi>5.</hi> H. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and was ſummoned to the Parliament as Lord <hi>Barkley.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tho. Lo. de la Ware</hi> died ſeized in taile by reaſon of a fine levied in the time of his Anceſtors, of the <hi>Baronie de la Ware</hi> with divers other lands in other Counties and died 5. <hi>H.</hi> 6 without iſſue; And <hi>Reginald Weſt,</hi> Knight of the halfe blood was next Heire,<note place="margin">Som. Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament. An <hi>7.</hi> H. <hi>6</hi>
                  </note> by reaſon of the intaile, And was ſummoned to the Parliament by the name of <hi>Regin. Lo. de la Ware</hi> Knight, although <hi>Iohn Griffeth</hi> was heire of the whole blood.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iohn de Vere,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſch. <hi>9.</hi> H <hi>6</hi> &amp; <hi>20.</hi> H. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> E. of <hi>Oxford,</hi> ſeized in his demeſne as of fee taile to him and to the Heires males of his body iſſuing of the Honour and County of
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:57614:42"/>
                  <hi>Oxford,</hi> with divers other lands <hi>A<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</hi> 18. <hi>H.</hi> 8. died without Heires of his body, and his three ſiſters (viz.) <hi>Elizab. Vrſula</hi> and <hi>Dorothy,</hi> were his next heire generall, but <hi>Iohn De Vere</hi> next heire male, was E. of <hi>Oxford,</hi> by reaſon of the ſaid intaile, and none of the ſaid three Heires obtained the dignitie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>William,</hi> Lord <hi>Paget,</hi> of <hi>Bewdſert,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſch. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no <hi>11.</hi> Eliz.</note> was ſeized in fee of the <hi>Baronies</hi> of <hi>Longden</hi> and <hi>Haywood,</hi> and of, and in the Mannors of <hi>Bewdſert Longden, &amp;c.</hi> and being ſo ſeized by fine, 1. <hi>Mar.</hi> intayled the Mannours and Baronies aforeſaid, to him and the Heires males of his body iſſuing, and after <hi>anno</hi> 5. <hi>Eliz.</hi> died leaving <hi>Hen.</hi> his Son next heire male, which <hi>Hen.</hi> entred into the Baronies and lands aforeſaid, by vertue of the aforeſaid fine and died thereof ſeized 11. <hi>Eliz.</hi> leaving <hi>Elizabeth</hi> his onely Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and heire, after whoſe death <hi>Tho. Paget,</hi> brother and heire male of the ſaid <hi>Hen.</hi> entred into the Baronies and Mannors aforeſaid, and was ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned to the Parliament by vertue of the aforeſaid fine.</p>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:57614:43"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Robert le Ogle</hi> intayled the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors of <hi>Bothall</hi> and <hi>Ogle,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſch. <hi>6.</hi> Eliz.</note> with divers other Mannors, <hi>&amp;c. Com. Northumb.</hi> to himſelfe for life, the Remainder to the Heires males of his body, and tooke to his firſt wife <hi>Dorothy Witherington,</hi> by whom he had iſſue <hi>Robert</hi> his eldeſt ſonne, and <hi>Margery</hi> his daughter mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried <hi>Gregory Ogle</hi> of <hi>Chippington,</hi> and the ſaid <hi>Rob.</hi> after the death of his firſt wife married <hi>Iohan Ratliffe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Brother of the half blood.</note> by whom he had iſſue <hi>Cuthbert</hi> his ſecond ſonne and died, after whoſe death <hi>Robt.</hi> the Sonne was Lord <hi>Ogle,</hi> and from him to <hi>Cuthbert</hi> brother of the halfe blood, by vertue of the intaile, and not vnto <hi>Marg.</hi> nor <hi>Cuthbert</hi> her ſonne of the whole blood.</p>
               <p>Moreover thirdly,<note place="margin">3. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion.</note> if a Baron by tenure doth Aliene by Licence to a meere ſtranger upon conſideration, or, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> if ſuch Alience be nobly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended in ſuch caſes, after ſuch alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, ſuch Alience hath borne the name and dignitie of a Baron, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of ſuch Barony ſo aliened; And if he had no Dignity before, hee in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of that hath beene ſummoned to
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:57614:43"/>the Parliament, and enjoyed the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rony hereof, are Preſidents extant.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Maude,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſch. <hi>22.</hi> Ric. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> Counteſſe of <hi>Angiers</hi> and <hi>Northumb.</hi> Heire of the Barony of <hi>Cockermouth,</hi> after the death of <hi>Lucy</hi> her Brother, who dyed without iſſue intailed the honour, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of <hi>Cocker-mouth</hi> to her ſelfe, and to <hi>Henry Pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi> Earle of <hi>Northumberland,</hi> then her Husband, and to the Heires males of their bodyes, upon condition that that ſhould beare the Armes of the ſaid Earle which are,<note place="margin">Armes gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</note> 
                  <hi>Or a Lyon rampant</hi> 6. <hi>quartered,</hi> with the Armes of <hi>Lucie (viz.) Gules</hi> 3. <hi>Lucies argent,</hi> bearing the ſaid Armes, ſo often as they ſhall appeare, and afterwards, <hi>viz.</hi> 22. <hi>R.</hi> 2. died without iſſue.</p>
               <p>Nevertheleſſe the ſaid Earle, and after him the ſaid <hi>Hen. Percy</hi> his Son were Barons of the ſaid Honour by the ſaid aſſurance, and Sir <hi>William Melton</hi> Knight, Couzen and next Heire of the ſaid Counteſſe never had the ſaid Armes.</p>
               <p>Amongſt the Parents in the Tower,<note place="margin">Chart pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent. in <hi>41.</hi> H <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 41. <hi>H.</hi> 3. it appearth that one <hi>Herward de Mariſco</hi> and <hi>Rameta</hi> his
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:57614:44"/>wife did grant unto <hi>Simon de Mount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort,</hi> then Earle of <hi>Leyceſter,</hi> the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rony of <hi>Elinden</hi> in the County of <hi>Northampton,</hi> which deſcended to the ſaid <hi>Rameta</hi> from <hi>John de Veſcount,</hi> which Graunt ſeemeth to be with Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, for that the ſaid King doth by his Patent confirme the ſame, and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther gave to the ſaid Earle and his Heires divers priviledges there.</p>
               <p>Alſo,<note place="margin">Exchange of a Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny.</note> this antient Charter follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing concerning the exchange of a Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rony with the King, is worthy me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, which is, K. <hi>Iohn a<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</hi> 7. granted unto <hi>Robert de Newbergh Fordington,</hi> for the honour of <hi>Burſtocke</hi> in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change, and granted that it ſhould be the head, and the chiefe of the Baron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, as <hi>Burſtock</hi> was aforetime, and that all Knights and others ſhould at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend upon him, and his lands in <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dington</hi> as chiefe of his Baronſhip, as they aforetime were attendant upon <hi>Robert Burſtock.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By theſe Preſidents appeareth, that Barony by tenure is <hi>annexa feodo.</hi> So that the former queſtions are fully ſatisfied and anſwered <hi>(viz.)</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:57614:44"/>
               <list>
                  <item>1. That by alienation without Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, the Barony is ferfeited.</item>
                  <item>2. The heires Males have enjoyed them, and the Females excluded.</item>
                  <item>3. That the Alience of ſuch a Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rony (nobly deſcended) is Baron.</item>
               </list>
               <p>But if ſuch alienation with Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence be made to any perſon ignoble,<note place="margin">Nora. 1.</note> though the burden of the tenure doth remaine on him for the K. beſt advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, yet he may not take upon him the Dignitie without the Kings ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall favour upon his merit.</p>
               <p>Upon conſideration therefore of theſe aſſertions all the former objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are anſwered, and as touching the firſt, it is anſwered by that which is laſt ſpecified, that an ignoble Alience may challenge nothing as a Baron by tenure.</p>
               <p>In 11. <hi>H.</hi> 4.2.6. in a Caſe concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Diſtreſſe, it is agreed that a Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron,<note place="margin">11. <hi>H.</hi> 4.2.6.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are not contributary for ſuch lands parcell of their Barony, but for other lands they are; but there is queſtion made, if one which is not Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron purchaſe a Barony, whether hee ſhall be diſcharged, which was not
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:57614:45"/>worthy the queſtioning, if ſuch a pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſer challenge by reaſon of his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe place in Parliament; For as land holden by villein ſervice, doth not make the owner a villein which doth purchaſe the ſame, although by tenure he muſt doe villein ſervice; So land holden by Baron ſervice doth not make the ignoble noble, though the charge of ſuch tenure lay upon him. Yet if the King will give to any man ignoble in recompence of ſervice any Caſtle, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to be holden <hi>per Baroniam,</hi> hee is forthwith noble, becauſe hee draweth this Nobilitie from the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine without other Creation.</p>
               <p>But a queſtion by the way what yeerely revenue is ſufficient for a Baron.<note place="margin">Qu.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Diverſitie of times hath brought forth divers determinations as touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the French conſtitution,<note place="margin">R.</note> there is an old Pamphlet wherein are theſe words; <hi>Summon. debeant omnes Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit. &amp; Barones, &amp; eorum pares (viz) qui habent terras &amp; reddit. ad valen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam Commitat. vel Baron. integre,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Modus te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nend. parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament.</note> 
                  <hi>viz.</hi> 20. <hi>feod. Milit. quolibet feod. comput.
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:57614:45"/>ad</hi> 12. <hi>librat. quae faciunt librat. vel ad valenc.</hi> 13. <hi>feod. Milit. &amp;</hi> 3. <hi>part. Vnius feodi Milit. quolibet feod. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putand. ad</hi> 20. <hi>librat. quae faciunt in toto</hi> 400. <hi>mercas, &amp; nulli minores laici ſommon. debeant ad Parliament. ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne tenur. niſi eorum praeſentia alijs de cauſis fuerit neceſſe (cap. du Laicis.)</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new of a Baron.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">Camden in Britann.</note> Others have eſteemed it to be foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene Knights Fees, but that doth reſt wholly in the pleaſure of the King to judge.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> To the ſecond, it is true that antient Baronies which were holden <hi>per Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roniam,</hi> are now in the hands of men ignoble, but the reaſon and meanes whereby ſuch Mannors ſhould thus come to the hands of meaner perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nages are twofold; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt,becauſe they have beene aliened by Licence to them. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, which was uſuall ſuch Mannors have upon divers rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons come to the Crowne by way of Reverſion, Eſcheat or forfeiture, and after they were conveyed to others, reſerving other ſervices, ſo that it is no wonder that they be now holden in Soccage, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:57614:46"/>
               <p> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>3</label> To the third Objection that antient Barons have aliened, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the degree, I anſwer, that it is true, yet it proveth nothing againſt the former reſolution, therefore conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that they be either originally Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons by Writ or by tenure; By Writ are of two kinds, for either in ſuch Writ whereby they or their Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors were at firſt Summoned, they were named only by their owne names; or elſe addition was given them from the principle place of their abode, either for ſome diſtinction to ſever them from ſome Honour of the ſame ſirname, or to give them ſuch honourable title by addition of the place which was not hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den <hi>per Baroniam,</hi> therefore if they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>llene it away, he may yet retaine the title becauſe it was not holden <hi>per Baroniam</hi> but was given by this Writ of ſummons; Thus much of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons by Writ.</p>
               <p>But if Baron by tenure aliene to one ignoble by licence, and after the alienor be called by Writ, he is not any more a Baron by tenure but by
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:57614:46"/>Writ and may retaine the name of a Baron. Now of Barons by Writ.</p>
               <p>A Baron by Writ is he to whom a Writ of ſummons is directed by the King to come to the Parliament to treat, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of the affaires of the Realme,<note place="margin">Barons by Writ.</note> the forme of which is, <hi>Rex,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">A Writ of Su<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp;c. A. B. &amp;c. de ſalut. quia de aviſamento conſilij noſtri pro quibuſdam arduis et vrgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus nos ſtatum &amp; defenſionem regni noſtri Angliae &amp; Eccleſiae Anglicanae concernent quoddam Parliament. noſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum apud, &amp;c. die, &amp;c. teneri ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vimus ac ibidem vobiſcum ac cum caete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris Praelatis, Magnatibus, &amp; proceribus dicti regni noſtri colloquium habere &amp; tractare vobis in fide &amp; legiantia veſtra quibus nobis tenemini. firmiter injun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gend. mandamus quod conſideratis di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorum negotiorum arduitate &amp; peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culis imminentibus ceſſante quacunque excuſatione dictis die, &amp; loco perſonali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter interſitis nobiſcum, ac cum Praelatis Magnat. ac Proceribus praedict. ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict. negotijs tractatur eſt urum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiliu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> impenſari, &amp; hoc ſicut nos &amp; honorem noſtrum &amp; ſalvationem &amp; defenſionem regni &amp; Eccle. praedict. expeditio neque
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:57614:47"/>dictorum negotiorum deligitis nullate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus omittatis;</hi> Which kind of Writ is as well directed to Barons by tenure and creation, as others which are one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Barons by Writ, which thereupon are to enjoy the dignitie, becauſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they be aſſociated in Counſell with the King, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Touching their antiquitie and their firſt inſtitution I find little or no mention before <hi>H.</hi> 3. his time,<note place="margin">Antiquity of Barons by Writ.</note> and therefore I conceive that either the firſt, or at leaſt the firſt frequent uſe of Barons by Writ was 49. <hi>H.</hi> 3. in caſe of neceſſitie and vpon lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table occaſion of civill warre about the great Charter, of which rebellion <hi>Simon</hi> then Earle of <hi>Leyceſter</hi> was ring-leader; And therfore after divers fields fought at <hi>Northampton, Rocheſter, Lewes,</hi> &amp;c. that of all was the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, of that tragedie finiſhed at <hi>Eveſham</hi> where the ſaid Earle was ſlaine and thoſe Rebellious Barons over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown; whereupon preſently iſſued the Parliament at <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> and after at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> where the ſaid Barons were to be attainted; Wherfore for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:57614:47"/>aſmuch as the number of the Barons which had continued faithfull was ſmall, it was holden a neceſſary po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie to ſupply the number, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> vpon ſummons by Writ where were called all Abbots, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which held not by Barony, as others of the moſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of the laytie not holding by Barony.</p>
               <p>Note further, theſe Writs in forme of their directions are divers,<note place="margin">Divers manners of directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of ſummons.</note> ſome directed by ſpeciall name of a Baron, as <hi>Rex Baroni de Staffe. de Greyſtock. de Dudley</hi> others by the name of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, with addition of the place, as <hi>Rex Iobanni de Straunge, de Knocking, Chr. Edm. Gray de Ruthen, Chr. Edw. Gray de Grooby, &amp;c.</hi> Naming the cheife Caſtle, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of ſuch Baron. ſome others are named in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner with the title of Lord, as <hi>Iohanni Beauchamp Domino de Beauch. Milit. Iohanni domino de Clinton; Hen. Percey, domino de Poynings;</hi> To others with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out additions, as <hi>William de Lourt Milit. Scals. Devereux.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the nature and qualitie of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Barons by Writ is aptly diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:57614:48"/>by debate of a queſtion concerning the continuance and deſcent of a Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rony by Writ, which I divide.</p>
               <p> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, whether a Barony by Writ may deſcend.</p>
               <p> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Admit it may then, whether it will to the heires females, there being no iſſue male.</p>
               <p> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Admit it doth then, whether the Husband of ſuch heire female may aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume the dignitie of a Baron in <hi>jure uxoris.</hi>
               </p>
               <p> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>1</label> Touching the firſt Queſtion, it ſhall be requiſite for ſatisfaction of all men, to alleadge ſuch principall rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons as are wont to bee produced of both parts.</p>
               <p> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <label>Argument. ex parte negat.</label> Nobilitie and honour given in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of wiſedome, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which are gifts of God, and perſonall cannot ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to others, for <hi>privilegium perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nale perſonam ſequitur &amp; extinguitur cum perſona,</hi> but ſuch is the dignitie of ſuch a Baron, therefore, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="The ſe∣cond."/> Againe, if the calling to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by Writ, be the efficient inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Nobilitie in the Anceſtor, then the not calling the heire is a loſſe
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:57614:48"/>of that Nobilitie. For admit ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of nature in the heire as leproſie Ideocy, Frenzie, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> he is made un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable, and thereupon they conclude that it ſhall not deſcend.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Argument. ex parte affirm.</label> Of the contrary part the affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive is proved thus, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Honour given in reſpect of wiſdome and vertue of him on whom it was firſt beſtowed is not onely a due reverence of him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> while he liveth, but alſo a memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable reward thereof to his poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; ſee <hi>Tully,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cicero pro Sextio.</note> Therefore this kind of honour is patrimoniall.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> If infamy of the anceſtor be a blot to poſteritie, as for it the law doth corrupt the blood for the offence of the Anceſtor, Reaſon would that the honour due to the Anceſtor, ſhould be likewiſe Honour to the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteritie; for Contraries doe carrie their contrary in reaſon; For determinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whereof it is to be noted that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſitie of reaſon hath bred diverſitie of opinions.</p>
               <p>Some thinke it is not deſcendable vnleſſe the Heire be likewiſe called by Writ, and that then its an inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:57614:49"/>but this is repugnant to the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of a deſcent, which commonly carieth the patrimony deſcendable (by act in law) vpon the death of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors (to the heire) or not at all, Wherefore divers preſidents prove that this doth deſcend, and there needs not any word of heire in the Writ of Summons, onely there is a ſpeech of a ſpeciall Writ ſometimes directed to Sir <hi>Henry Bromflet,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Teſte Rege apud Weſt. <hi>24</hi> Iun. <hi>27.</hi> H <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> when he was called Lo. <hi>Veſcy</hi> by <hi>H.</hi> 8. in 27. yeere of his raigne, wherein there are theſe words inſerted, <hi>Volumus ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men vos &amp; haeredes veſtros maſculos de corpore veſtro legitime exeuntes Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes de Veſcye.</hi> Wherfore it is ever true that the heire of ſuch a Baron when he is called to the Parliament, that his deſcent of honour is thereby eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and approved by the gratious Iudgment of our Soveraigne: ſo it is alſo true that if it ſhall ſtand with her highneſſe pleaſure that ſuch heire ſhall not be ſummoned at all (for none come to ſo high a Councell ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept he be called) then that Nobilitie is much impaired and in manner extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:57614:49"/>in the cenſure of all men, for that it had no other originall, but by writ of Summons, for the which in the Judgement of the ſupreme Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, he is ſecluded. And thus much as concerning the firſt Article or point touching the deſcent in generall of this kind of Baronie.</p>
               <p>As for the ſecond principall Point,<note place="margin">The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond point.</note> whether the Barony by Writ may deſcend to the heire Male, it ſhall not be amiſſe likewiſe to view the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of each part, that by the conflict of Argument the truth may the better be diſcerned.</p>
               <p>Thoſe which doe maintaine the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmative part doe reaſon after this manner;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ratio</hi> 1. On the affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive part.</note> In reaſon the ſexe of the Heire female ought no more to barre her of the dignitie then the nonage of the Heire male ought to barre him, although during his nonage hee be not able to doe the ſervice; But as the ſervice of the one is forbearing for the time; So the ſexe of the other may at all times be ſupplyed by the maturi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and ſufficiencie of her husband.<note place="margin">Ratio. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>Offices of Honour which doe much
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:57614:50"/>import the publike weale being poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed by inheritance to deſcend to the heire female, if there bee no Neeces heire male, as the office of high Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable of <hi>England,</hi> which deſcended unto the Daughter of <hi>Humfrey de Bohun</hi> Earle of <hi>Hereford</hi> and <hi>Eſſex,</hi> as afore declared, the office of Lord Steward, deſcended unto <hi>Blanch</hi> Daughter of <hi>Henry</hi> Earle of <hi>Lanca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> in whoſe right <hi>Iohn of Gaunt</hi> her Husband enjoyed the ſame. The like may be ſaid of the Office of Earle Marſhall which deſcended by an Heire female unto the houſe of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folke.</hi> All which Offices are as unfit to be exerciſed by a woman, as it is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit for a woman to bee ſummoned to the Parliament as a Baron by Writ. And yet notwithſtanding the Law doth allow the Husband of ſuch a woman to exerciſe the Office of the one; And therefore by the ſame con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruitie of reaſon ſuch Husband is likewiſe by law inabled to performe the other.<note place="margin">Ratio <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>Many Noble houſes in <hi>England</hi> doe ſupport, and lawfully beare the Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:57614:50"/>of Baronage unto them deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by women,<note place="margin">Renatus: Cap nus de dom. cap. H. <hi>7.</hi> &amp; <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> of the which many are by Writ. Moreover, in <hi>France</hi> the dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie to be a Peere of the Realme (as <hi>Opimus</hi> by many examples proveth deſcendeth to the heire female for want of heire male.</p>
               <p>The dignitie of Nobilitie deſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth likewiſe in <hi>Spaine</hi> vnto the female for want of Heire male which cuſtome not being onely currant in our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour countries, but with vs in an evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent proofe in the caſe in queſtion.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ratio</hi> 1. on the Negat.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The adverſe part object that the writ of ſummons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by which the Baron hath his originall, is to call him to be one of the members of that right high aſſemby of Parliament there to determine life and member, plea and right of land, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but theſe things are convenient onely for the qualitie of men, not to the other ſexe, <hi>Ergo,</hi> it not to deſcend to the heire female.<note place="margin">Ratio. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>If it be anſwered that ſuch heire fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male be unfit in her owne perſon, yet may ſhe marry one fufficiently able to excecute the ſame, this anſwer will neither ſatisfie nor ſalve the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenience,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:57614:51"/>for admit ſhe were at age at the death of her Anceſtors vnmarried being in her owne choice, the great cauſes of the Realme ſhould be ſubject to her will in the choiſe of her Husband which were incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient.</p>
               <p> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ratio. </seg>3</label> Thirdly if ſuch husband bee ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned the writ ſhould make meantion thereof, for otherwiſe it may be taken that he was choſen in his owne perſon and not in her right, but ſuch a Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons wherein the wife was menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned was never ſeene and if by a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall writ without mentioning his wife, hee is thereby made Baron in his owne right.</p>
               <p> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſer. </seg>1</label> Having heard the arguments on both ſides, place doth now require that we ſhould interpoſe opinion to compound this controverſie, This queſtion is ſomewhat perplexed by different Preſidents, for ſome Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents prove that Baronies by Writ have deſcended to Heires females, whoſe Husbands have beene called to the Parliament, whether in their owne or Wives right it matters not;
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:57614:51"/>but ſure it is that ſuch Marriage gave occaſion to the Summons, and ſuch Husbands and their poſterities beare the dignitie of the wives Anceſtors, for by this controverſie wee purpoſe not to queſtion the right of ſuch No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble houſes.</p>
               <p> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſer. </seg>2</label> Secondly, wee muſt acknowledge that the Qu. is to ſummon to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament whom ſhe pleaſe, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whereas <hi>Rodulph</hi> Lord <hi>Cromell</hi> being a Baron by Writ died having two Coheires,<note place="margin">Barony of <hi>Cromwell.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Eliz.</hi> married to Sir <hi>Thomas Nevill,</hi> and <hi>Ioan</hi> the younger to Sir <hi>Humfrey Bourchier,</hi> the ſaid Sir <hi>Humphrey</hi> was called to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament as Lord <hi>Cromwell,</hi> and not Sir <hi>Thomas Nevill,</hi> who had married the eldeſt Siſter.</p>
               <p> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſer. </seg>3</label> That if a Baron by Writ die, his Daughter, Siſter, or other collaterall Heire female being his Heire, and that no collaterall Heire male can chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge the ſaid Barony by any antient intayle or otherwiſe, ſuch claim by the Heire female hath heretofore beene allowed by the late right Honourable Commiſſioners in the office of the
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:57614:52"/>Early Marſhall ſignified to the Queen, as upon the Petition of the Siſter, and Heire of <hi>Gregory</hi> late Lord <hi>Dacres,</hi> deceaſed may appeare; In whoſe Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>degree it appeares, that <hi>Thomas</hi> Lord <hi>Dacres,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Barony of <hi>Dacres.</hi>
                  </note> had iſſue <hi>Thomas</hi> his eldeſt Sonne, <hi>Ralph</hi> his ſecond, and <hi>Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrey</hi> his third; <hi>Thomas</hi> died in the life of his Father having iſſue <hi>Jone</hi> his Daughter and heire, married to Sir <hi>Richard Fines,</hi> after <hi>Tho.</hi> the Grandfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther died, wherevpon <hi>H.</hi> 6. by Patent 7. <hi>Novemb. Anno</hi> 37. declares the ſaid <hi>Richard Fines</hi> to be Lo. <hi>Dacres,</hi> but <hi>tempore E.</hi> 4. the ſaid <hi>Humf. Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cres</hi> after the Attainder of the ſaid <hi>Ralph</hi> &amp; himſelfe by Parliament 1 <hi>E.</hi> 4 and after of the ſaid <hi>Ralph</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall of the ſaid act in 12. <hi>E.</hi> 4. the ſaid <hi>Humf.</hi> challenged the Baronie, whereupon after it was controverted in Parliament, they ſubmitted them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the arbitrement of <hi>E.</hi> 4. for performance whereof they entered bond, whereupon the King awarded vnder the privy Seale,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Award</hi> by King <hi>E.</hi> 4.</note> 8. <hi>Aprill Anno</hi> 13. that the ſaid <hi>Richard Fines</hi> ſhould be reputed Lo. <hi>Dacres,</hi> and
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:57614:52"/>that he and his Heires of the body of the ſaid <hi>Richard</hi> ſhould retaine the ſaid place in Parliament, which the ſaid <hi>Tho.</hi> Lo. <hi>Dacres</hi> uſed, And that the heires of the body of the ſaid <hi>Tho.</hi> ſhould enjoy the Mannor of <hi>Holbeck.</hi> And that the ſaid <hi>Humf. Dacres</hi> ſhould be reputed, named, and called the Lo. <hi>Dacres</hi> of <hi>Gilleſland,</hi> And that hee, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſhould keepe the place in Parliament next beneath the ſaid <hi>Richard Fines, &amp;c.</hi> And that the heires of the ſaid <hi>Tho. Dacres</hi> ſhould have the Mannor of <hi>Fethington, &amp;c.</hi> in Taile.<note place="margin">Nota.</note> And ſo note that <hi>Gilleſtand</hi> the antient Barony remained to the heire male.</p>
               <p> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſer. </seg>4</label> Obſerve alſo, that if any Baron doe die without iſſue male, and that by ſome ſpeciall intaiſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by which an heire female enjoyeth the inheritance of the ſaid Baron, ſuch heires females have beene called to the Parliament, and not the husband or iſſue male of of ſuch heire female, and this appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth by a notable controverſie <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore H.</hi> 7. between Sir <hi>Robert Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loughbie</hi> Lo. <hi>Brooke,</hi> and <hi>Richard
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:57614:53"/>Nevill</hi> Lo. <hi>Latimer,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Barony of <hi>Latimer.</hi>
                  </note> for the Barony of <hi>Latimer,</hi> which in effect was, The ſaid Lo. <hi>Brooke</hi> challenged the ſaid Barony as coſen and heire of <hi>Eliz.</hi> his great grandmother, who was ſiſter and heire to <hi>Iohn Nevill</hi> Lo. <hi>Latimer,</hi> who died without iſſue, And here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon exhibited a Petition to <hi>H.</hi> 7. in Parliament, whereunto <hi>Richard</hi> then Lo. <hi>Latimer</hi> was called to anſwer, who agreed the deſcent <hi>(viz.)</hi> that the ſaid <hi>Eliz.</hi> was married vnto Sir <hi>Tho. Willoughbie,</hi> ſecond Sonne to the Lo. <hi>Willoughbie,</hi> but <hi>H.</hi> 6. becauſe the ſaid <hi>Iohn</hi> died without iſſue, and that the next heire was female, did there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore call to the Parliament Sir <hi>George Nevill,</hi> ſecond ſonne of <hi>Ralph</hi> Earle of <hi>Weſtmerland</hi> to be Lo. <hi>Latimer,</hi> which <hi>George</hi> was grandfather of the ſaid <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard,</hi> namely Father of <hi>Hen.</hi> father to the ſaid <hi>Richard,</hi> in debate of which cauſe our Queſtion, <hi>viz.</hi> whether a Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rony by Writ may deſcend vnto heires females was debated, and in the end adjudged with the ſaid <hi>Rich.</hi> which Preſidents doe afford vs 2. Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in the point.</p>
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:57614:53"/>
               <p> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> But here the former Preſident of the Barony of <hi>Dacres,</hi> may be objected to incounter this concluſion: for whereas the heire female married to Sir <hi>Rich. Fines,</hi> he was Baron of <hi>Dacres,</hi> and <hi>Raynolph</hi> and <hi>Humf.</hi> the heires males placed below the ſaid heire female by <hi>H.</hi> 6. and <hi>E.</hi> 4.</p>
               <p> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> This Objection is eaſily anſwered, for although <hi>H.</hi> 6. did declare him Lo. <hi>Dacres.</hi> yet <hi>Rand.</hi> being heire male bare alſo the title of Lo. <hi>Dacres,</hi> and by that name was attainted 1. <hi>E.</hi> 4</p>
               <p>Wherefore the Reaſon why the heire male could not be regarded was the attainder,<note place="margin">Ratio.</note> and when this was reverſed <hi>E.</hi> 4. to ſatisfie both com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petitors thus orderd it. And thus much concerning the ſecond point whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a Barony by writ may deſcend unto the heire female.</p>
               <p>Concerning the third point admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſuch deſcent to their female,<note place="margin">The third Article.</note> when no male can claime it, for then doth this queſtion take place whether her husband ſhould enjoy that digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in her right or no, ſomething hath beene ſaid hereof in the laſt queſtion,</p>
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:57614:54"/>
               <p>But for ſatisfaction wee are to inſiſt upon a reſolution in the very point <hi>tempore H.</hi> 8. When Maſter <hi>Wimbiſh</hi> tooke upon him the ſtile of Lord <hi>Tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bois, jure uxoris</hi> having no iſſue by her, The King aſſiſted both by civill and temporall Lawyers gave ſentence,<note place="margin">Reſolution <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cmp. H. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> that no husband of a Baroneſſe ſhould uſe her ſtile untill he had by her a child, whereby he ſhould be intitled by the curteſie to her inheritance.</p>
               <p> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ratio. </seg>1</label> The ſpeciall reaſons that occaſioned this ſentence were 2. firſt, the incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience that the husband ſhould be a Peere of the Realme to day, and to morrow by the death of his wife none, and ſo honour ſubject to mutation without default of the partie.</p>
               <p> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ratio. </seg>2</label> Secondly, if he had iſſue, if he ſhould not beare the ſtile, then ſhould his Son after the death of his Mother, dying in the life of his Father, bee a Baron without land, for it the Father hath by the curteſie: but theſe queſtions take place where there is no Heire male at all.</p>
               <p>And thus much concerning the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, qualitie, and eſtate of the Baron
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:57614:54"/>by Writ, and for reſolution of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall points and articles of the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion propoſed may ſuffice, onely note the Caſe in 13. <hi>E.</hi> 3. where <hi>William de Clinton</hi> having married the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſe of <hi>Huntington,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">13. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>Briefe</hi> 259.</note> they joyned in an Aſſiſe of <hi>Nuſance</hi> for levying a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Exception was taken, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he did not name himſelfe, but it was over-ruled, becauſe having it <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re Vxoris,</hi> by the Law he may not uſe the ſame title, having no other title thereunto.</p>
               <p>Now come we to Barons by Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent.</p>
               <p>A Baron by Creation,<note place="margin">Barons by Patent.</note> is he or ſhee to whom the King hath conferred Baronies by his Letters Patents.</p>
               <p>The uſuall words are, <hi>Conſiderantes ita<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> generis claritat. vel grata obſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quia quae A.B. Mil. nobis praeſtiterit,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Sciatis nos,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>praefat. A.B. ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatum, gradum, dignitat. &amp; honor. Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronis te ereximus praefecerimus &amp; crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vimus eidem<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> A.B. nomen,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis de T. impoſuimus,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Ac per pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentes damus,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>habend. praefat. A.B. &amp; Haer.</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:57614:55"/>
               <p>This kind of Dignitie ſhall bee of ſuch continuance, as ſhall be limited in the <hi>Habend.</hi> ſometimes for life, ſometimes <hi>pur auter vie,</hi> as ſome hold opinion in 32. <hi>H.</hi> 6.<note place="margin">32. <hi>H.</hi> 6.296</note> It may bee in the ſpeciall or in the generall. And this kind of Patent was uſuall before the Statute of 2. as it apeareth by the Patent,<note place="margin">Pat. <hi>13</hi> H. <hi>3.</hi> in turre, p. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> whereby <hi>Hugh de Burga</hi> was made Earle of <hi>Kent,</hi> in the time of <hi>H.</hi> 3. which was <hi>Habend. ſibi &amp; haered. ſuis de corpore Margaret uxoris ſuae ſororis Alexandri Regis Scociae procreat. &amp; pro defectu talis exitus reman. Rici<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s haered. dicti Hugonis</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The manner of the Solemnitie uſed in the Creation of Barons by Patent,<note place="margin">The forme of Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a Baron.</note> is much after this forme; The Baron newly to be Created, is preſented un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Queenes Majeſtie ſitting in her Chaire of ſtate; After this order he is apparelled; In his Surcote with the hood, a Baron bearing the mantle be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, and two Barons in their Parliament robes, on each hand one leading him. The principall King at Armes bearing the Patent, and the Officers at armes proceeding on be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:57614:55"/>him; when they come in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of her Majeſtie, they make their ſolemne obeyſance three times; And the Baron to be Created kneeleth downe before the Chaire of Eſtate, the ſaid King at Armes delivereth the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of Creation to the Lord Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlaine, who humbly preſents the ſame to her Majeſtie, who delivereth the ſame to the principall Secretary to bee read, who reading the ſame with a loud voyce at the word <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vimus,</hi> the Baron which carrieth the Mantle, preſenteth the ſame to her Majeſtie, who puts it on the new Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron, whereby he is Created, and then is the Patent read out to the end, and delivered to the Queene, who delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth it to the Baron ſo Created, who after moſt humble thankes given to her Majeſty, hee riſeth up, and they depart in like ſolemne order, as they came with the Trumpets ſounding be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them. The particular &amp; more full knowledge of theſe Solemnities I doe referre to the Colledge and Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Heraulds, to whom the knowledge of theſe things doth
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:57614:56"/>moſt ſpecially appertaine.</p>
               <p>For the better explanation of this kind of Dignitie, the reſolution alſo of certaine queſtions ſhall bee very requiſite.</p>
               <p> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>1</label> Firſt, if a Nobleman and his Proge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitors have for a long time beene cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to the Parliament, and he a Baron either by tenure or by Writ, And have had in regard thereof a place certaine in Parliament, if afterwards the ſame Noble man ſhall be created a Baron of that Barony, and by the ſame name by Letters Patents, whether ſhall he and his heires retaine his old place in Parliament, which he had according to the former dignitie, or whether ſhall he loſe his old place and take a new place, according to the time of his creation onely.</p>
               <p>The caſe of the Lord <hi>De la Ware</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived a reſolution ſome what anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to this Queſtion,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>De laware,</hi> 11. <hi>Rep.</hi> Looke fol 1. <hi>E.</hi> 3 6.</note> The Lord <hi>De la Ware</hi> 3. <hi>E.</hi> 6. being in ſore diſpleaſure, which <hi>William Weſt</hi> his Nephew and heire, who was father to <hi>Tho.</hi> now Lord <hi>De la Ware</hi> procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red an act of Parliament, by the which
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:57614:56"/>the ſaid <hi>William Weſt</hi> was during his naturall life onely, cleerely diſabled to claime, demand, or have any manner of right, Title, or intereſt by deſcent, remainder, or otherwiſe in, or to the Mannors, Lands, tenents, or heredita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, title or dignitie of <hi>Tho.</hi> Lo. <hi>de la Ware</hi> his vncle, And after the ſaid <hi>Tho.</hi> Lo. <hi>De la Ware</hi> died and the ſaid <hi>William Weſt</hi> in the time of Qu. <hi>Mary</hi> was attainted of treaſon by verdict,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>2.</hi> &amp; <hi>3</hi> Ph. &amp; Mary. <hi>5.</hi> Eliz.</note> and afterwards pardoned by Q. <hi>Mary,</hi> and after by Parliament in the time of the O. Mareſtie that now is. And after in 8. <hi>Eliz.</hi> was created Lo. <hi>De la Ware</hi> by Patent, and had place in the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament according to his creation, For that by the ſaid act of Parliament in the time of <hi>E.</hi> 6. hee was excluded to challenge the ſormer auntient Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rony, and after died, whether the now Lo. <hi>De la Ware</hi> ſhould take his place according to the Baron by Writ, or according to his creation was the queſtion. The opinions of the Qu. Councell being her Maieſties Attorny generall, and Solliciter were that the acceptance of the new creation by
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:57614:57"/>the ſaid <hi>William Weſt,</hi> could not extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh the antient dignity, for he had not that antient Dignitie in him at the time of his Creation, but that Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie was at the time of his Creation by the Act of <hi>E.</hi> 6. in abbeyance, ſuſpence or conſideration of law, and he there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by utterly diſ-inabled to have the ſame during his life onely, ſo as his acceptance could not extinguiſh that dignitie which he then had not nor could conclude his heire, who was not diſabled by the ſaid act of 3. <hi>E.</hi> 6. to claime the antient Barony, which opinion of theirs was ſoone allowed by the reſolutions of the Lo. cheife Iuſtice of <hi>Engl.</hi> and Lord cheife Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron, and ſo ſignified to the Lord Kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. But this to be noted by the reaſons made for the ſaid reſolution, That if the ſaid Sir <hi>William Weſt</hi> had beene Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron, and intitled,<note place="margin">Nota.</note> or in poſſeſſion of the antient dignitie when he accepted the creation, the law perchance might have beene otherwiſe, but that remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth as yet unreſolved.</p>
               <p> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>2</label> Secondly, it may be queſtioned whether a Baron called by Patent
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:57614:57"/>ought to be named by the name of his dignitie, in every Writ to be ſued by him, or againſt him.</p>
               <p>The bookes of law doe make dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference herein betweene Duke, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe,<note place="margin">8. <hi>H.</hi> 6.10. 30 <hi>H.</hi> 8.30</note> Earle, Viſcount, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which are allowed names of Dignitie and the Baron, for they affirme that ſuch Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron needeth not to be named Lord or Baron by his Writ, but the Duke, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe, Earle or Viſcount, ought to be named by their Names or Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; Nevertheleſſe I doe take theſe bookes to be underſtood of the Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny by tenure, or Barons by Writ one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for the title of a Baron by Patent in his Letters Patents under Seale ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and named by the name of <hi>Status, gradus &amp; dignitas,</hi> and therefore is requiſite to be named, and ſuch digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are a parcell of the name of the poſſeſſor, as well as the Title and Stile of Duke, Marqueſſe, Earle, Viſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And although there may be concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved this difference laſt mentioned be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Baron by tenure or Writ, and the Baron by Patent, yet they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:57614:58"/>all members of the higher houſe of the Parliament, they are thereby e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually made Noble, Honourable, and Peeres of the Realme, as they are Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons onely, without any other di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction that I have obſerved. And thus much concerning the three de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of Barons within this Realme may ſuffice to be ſaid in generall upon this occaſion, for the better under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding and reſolution of the contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie in hand.<note place="margin">The pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge of Barons.</note>
               </p>
               <p>There reſteth laſt of all in this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of Baronage that I would ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe ſome certaine of the ſundry priviledges that the Lawes doe allow unto Barons, and the Nobilitie of the Realm ingenerall, in regard of that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, which all good policy in every wel-governed Common-wealth doth beſtow and yeeld to the Noble and Honourable, wherein I ſhall content my ſelfe onely with certaine of thoſe priviledges which I find mentioned in the Lawes of this Realme, purpoſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly omitting ſuch as either the Civill, Common, or the lawes of forraigne Countries doe afford, referring them
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:57614:58"/>to a fit place in an intended Treatiſe of Nobilitie.<note place="margin">Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt therefore it is a priviledge that the Peeres and Nobilitie of the Parliament doe enjoy, namely to bee tried in the caſes of Treaſon, Felony,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mag. Char.</hi> 29 10. <hi>E.</hi> 4.6.20. <hi>H.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 9</note> and ſuch like by their Peeres.</p>
               <p>The antiquitie and originall of this kind of triall hath (as ſome men doe thinke) his ground from the Statute of <hi>Magna Charta, cap.</hi> 29. beginning that <hi>Nullus liber homo,</hi> in theſe words, <hi>Nec ſuper eum ibimus, nec ſuper eum mittimus niſi per legale judicium Pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um ſuorum.</hi> But I take it to be more antient,<note place="margin">Triall by Peeres Where al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowable <hi>De conſuet. feudorum.</hi>
                  </note> as brought into this Realme with the Conquerour, being anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to the Norman and French lawes, and agreeable with the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes ſeverall, where almoſt all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies ariſing betweene the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne and his Peeres are tried, <hi>per judicium Parium ſuorum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Triall in antient time was very oft had in Parliament as may bee collected by the Statute of 15. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 6.<note place="margin">15. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 6.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>H.</hi> 4.1. 13 <hi>H.</hi> 8.11</note> But nevertheleſſe the ſame may as well be performed by Commiſſion
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:57614:59"/>under the Lord Steward of <hi>Eng.</hi> the forme, manner, and Solemnitie wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is expreſſed in the bookes of Law.</p>
               <p>This priviledge hath ſome reſtraint, as well in regard of the perſon,<note place="margin">The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint of the pravi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</note> as in the manner of proceedings. As touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the perſon.</p>
               <p> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, the Archbiſhops of this Realme, although they bee Lords of the Parliament, if they bee im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peached of ſuch aſſent as aforeſaid, ſhall not be tried by the Peeres of this Realme, but by a Jury of other ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiall perſons upon their oathes, the reaſon thereof (as I can conceive) as before remembred,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>27.</hi> H. <hi>8.</hi> Br. Inqueſt. <hi>100</hi> Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all <hi>142.</hi> Fine <hi>2.</hi> Stamf. <hi>153</hi>
                  </note> namely for as much as the Archbiſhops and Biſhops cannot paſſe in the like caſes upon the tryall of any other of the Peeres, for that they are prohibited by the Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall lawes to bee judges of life and blood, reaſon would that the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Peeres ſhould not trie them: for this triall ſhould be mutuall for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as it is performed upon their Honour without any oath taken.</p>
               <p> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, as touching the perſon,<note place="margin">38. <hi>H.</hi> 6. <hi>Br.</hi> Treaſon.</note> none but Lords of the Laytie being
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:57614:59"/>Lords of the Parliament,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>38.</hi> H <hi>8.</hi> Caſe Leo. Grey en le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Con.</note> ſhall have this kind of Triall. And therefore hereout are excluded the eldeſt Sonne and heire apparent of a Duke, in the life of his Father, though he be called Earle &amp; beare that title, Likewiſe, the eldeſt Sonne and Heire apparent of an Earle, though he be onely a Lord, or Baron, or beare ſuch Title.</p>
               <p> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thoſe that are Barons, and of the Nobility of <hi>Ireland,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">19 <hi>&amp;</hi> 20. <hi>Eliz</hi> 36.6.</note> if upon the like offence committed in <hi>Engl.</hi> if they chance to be apprehended in <hi>Engl.</hi> they ſhall not be tried herein by their Peeres, For the Lords of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of <hi>England</hi> are not their Peeres, but the Lords of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in <hi>Ireland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And thus much concerning the Reſtraints of the ſaid priviledges in reſpect of the perſon.</p>
               <p>As touching the manner of Procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Nobilitie of this Realme doe injoy the priviledge of triall by their Peeres in Courſe of Inditement onely,<note place="margin">33. <hi>H</hi> 8. <hi>Br. Iurors,</hi> 48. <hi>Triall.</hi> 142. 10 <hi>E.</hi> 3.6. <hi>Stam</hi> 152.</note> which is a kind of proceeding <hi>ex officio</hi> between the Qu. highneſſe and them, But in any caſe of Appeale of felony,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:57614:60"/>which is in the ſuite of the ſubject, they ſhall not have the ſame, but ſhall be tried by a Jury of 12. men upon their oathes. And thus much concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this priviledge at this place, and upon this occaſion may ſuffice.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe this priviledge the Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of this Realme doe enjoy,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Privilegiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſecundum.</hi> 48. <hi>E.</hi> 3.30 48. <hi>Aſſiſ.</hi> 6. 35 <hi>H.</hi> 6.46 22. <hi>H.</hi> 8.22 <hi>Reg.</hi> 1 79. 15 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 315.</note> That they are not ſo to be inpannelled in any Jury or inqueſt, to make triall or inquiry upon their corporall oathes between partie and partie, And if they be impannelled contrary thereunto, they may have a writ out of the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery repeating this priviledge di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to the Iuſtices, before whom ſuch noble perſonages are impan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelled, commanding them to diſſmiſſe him or them, that were ſo impannel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led out of the ſaid Pannell.</p>
               <p>This priviledge hath reſtraint in two caſes,<note place="margin">Reſtraint. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> firſt if he inquire concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the King and Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon-wealth in any neceſſary and important Decrees, as buſineſſe of this Realme, then this priviledge is not allowed, nor taketh place. And therefore divers Barons of the Marches of Wales, were im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nelled
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:57614:60"/>before the Biſhop of <hi>Ely,</hi> and other Commiſſioners of <hi>Oyer</hi> and <hi>Terminer,</hi> to inquire of notable outrage committed by <hi>Gilbe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t de Clare,</hi> Earle of <hi>Glouceſter,</hi> againſt <hi>Humfrey de Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hun,</hi> Earle of <hi>Pereford</hi> and <hi>Eſſex,</hi> and his ſuits in <hi>Wales</hi> in the 20. yeere of <hi>E.</hi> 1. where <hi>Iohn de Haſtings, Edmond de Mortimer, Theobald de Verdune,</hi> and other of the Barons of the March<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s of <hi>Wales</hi> challenged their priviledges aforeſaid, and much inſiſted upon the ſame, but it was afterwards anſwered by the Court, as by the words of the appeareth,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>20</hi> E. <hi>1.</hi> Rel. <hi>14.</hi> Camera. Scar.</note> 
                  <hi>Eo quod res iſt a dominum Regem &amp; coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam &amp; dignitatem ſuos tangit deinde fuit ex parte domini Regis Ioha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nt Haſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. &amp; omnibus alijs magnat. ſupra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominat. quod pro ſtatu &amp; jure regnt, &amp; Pro conſervatione dignitatis Coronae, &amp; pacis ſuae opponant manum, ad li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brum, ad faciend. &amp;c. quod eis ex parte Domini Regis injungentur, &amp;c.</hi> The Barons aforeſaid nevertheleſſe did perſiſt in their Challenge, and in the end both the ſaid Earle, betweene whom the ſaid outrage had heene per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petrated,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:57614:61"/>ſubmitted themſelves to the Kings grace, and made their Fines.</p>
               <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">Reſtraint <hi>2</hi>
                  </note> this priviledge hath no place in caſe of neceſſitie, where the truth can no otherwiſe come to light, for the Writ is,<note place="margin">Regiſt. <hi>179.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Quia Barones in Aſſiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis jurat. &amp;c. poni non conſuêrunt. ut dicunt niſi eorum Sacrament. adeo ſit neceſſarium quod ſine illis verit as in qua non poſſit, tibi praecepimus, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In many Caſes the Proteſtation of honour ſhall ſatisfie in Noblemen,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Privileg.</hi> 3. <hi>Bract. l.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 9. <hi>fol.</hi> 352.8.3.1. <hi>H.</hi> 4.1.13 <hi>H.</hi> 8.1 3 <hi>H.</hi> 6.48. <hi>Cooke</hi> 6.53</note> as in triall of their Peeres, they proceed upon their honour, not upon their oath. And if a Nobleman on an action of debt upon an Accompt, in caſe where the Plaintife is to be examined upon oath, upon the Statute of 5. <hi>H.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 8. it ſhall ſuffice to examine his Attorney, and not himſelfe upon his oath.</p>
               <p>Yet if a Nobleman will give evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to a Jury, reaſon would that he ſhould bee ſworne, for they are not bound to beleeve him upon ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation otherwiſe then they thinke in their conſcience to be conformable unto truth.</p>
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:57614:61"/>
               <p> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> If a man doth receive a menace at the hand of a Nobleman,<note place="margin">Privileg.</note> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he conceiveth feare of his ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard,<note place="margin">35 <hi>H</hi> 6. <hi>Sub-paena</hi> 20 <hi>V.</hi> 14. <hi>E.</hi> 3.</note> and prayes a <hi>Supplicavit</hi> in the Chan. directed unto the Juſtice of peace, or Sheriffe to take bond, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſuch Writ which otherwiſe is ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, but the Lord Chancellour ſhall award a <hi>Sub-paena</hi> in ſtead thereof, and when he appeareth in ſtead of ſurety, he ſhall onely promiſe upon his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to keepe the peace, which the Law hath allowed in this point a Caution ſufficient.</p>
               <p>A nobleman is not to bee arreſted by any <hi>Capias,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Privileg.</hi> 5. 21. <hi>E.</hi> 3.39. 43. <hi>E.</hi> 3.33. 8 <hi>R</hi> 2 7. <hi>H.</hi> 4 2. 11. <hi>H.</hi> 4.15 1. <hi>H.</hi> 5.14. 14. <hi>H.</hi> 6.2. 22 <hi>H.</hi> 6.226. 26. <hi>H</hi> 8.7. 14. <hi>Eliz</hi> 115. <hi>Reſtaint.</hi>
                  </note> and therefore cannot be outlawed in any civill Action, but onely in Criminall.</p>
               <p>And by the ſame reaſon lyeth no At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tachment againſt him, as it was ruled in Parliament, 14. <hi>Eliz.</hi> in the Lord <hi>Cromwells</hi> Caſe.</p>
               <p>But if he make any notable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt againſt the proceedings, of the Law, then ceaſeth this priviledge, for <hi>Fruſtra legis auxilium invocat, qui in legem peccat.</hi> As if in a Writ <hi>de homine replegiando,</hi> hee will not permit the
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:57614:62"/>Sheriffe to execute the Writ or Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoigne the party, or upon a Reſcouſſe a <hi>Capias</hi> hath this priviledge notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.</p>
               <p>So in caſes Criminall,<note place="margin">27. <hi>H.</hi> 8.14 15. <hi>H.</hi> 7.1.</note> a <hi>Capias</hi> and an <hi>Exigent</hi> may be awarded.</p>
               <p>The like priviledges doth the Court of equitie allow in caſes of conſcience,<note place="margin">Chanc. no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine Sub-paena.</note> for the Lord Chancellour doth not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward any Sub-paena, but ſendeth his Letters miſſive in lieu of other ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Proceſſe.</p>
               <p>In the proſecution of any Action perſonall,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Privil.</hi> 6. 14 <hi>E.</hi> 3.22. 15 <hi>E.</hi> 3.21 22 <hi>E.</hi> 3.9. 27. <hi>E.</hi> 38. 41. <hi>E</hi> 3.31 27 <hi>H.</hi> 8.22</note> the Plaintife may pray <hi>Jour de grace,</hi> but againſt a Peere of the Realme, it ſhall not be allowed, although it be allowable againſt other perſons.</p>
               <p>If any Lord Spirituall or Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall be partie to any Action,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Privileg.</hi> 7. 13. <hi>E</hi> 3.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Chal.</hi> 115.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 22. <hi>H</hi> 8.22 <hi>Dyer.</hi> 107.3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 4. <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lize</hi> 24 9. <hi>&amp;</hi> 10. <hi>Eliz.</hi> 26.</note> there ought to be one Knight at the leaſt, to be impannelled in his Jury, with other the moſt ſufficienteſt Eſquires in the Countrey, otherwiſe he may chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge the Array, but if there bee no Knight in the County, the Pannell ſhal be made of the moſt ſufficient <hi>Vava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours</hi> and Eſquires there inhabiting.</p>
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:57614:62"/>
               <p>But if one bring an Action againſt another, and the Sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>riffe impannell a Jury, where there is not any Knight,<note place="margin">14. <hi>&amp;</hi> 15. <hi>Eliz.</hi> 318.</note> and before the Triall the Plaintife or Defendant is Created a Baron, or, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and hee doe challenge the ſaid Jury, ſuch challenge ſhall not bee allowed, for at the time of the enqueſt made, he was not ſo reputed, as in the Caſe of <hi>Reginald,</hi> late Earle of <hi>Kent</hi> may appeare.</p>
               <p>If the King grant an Annuitie or Rent, to a then created Baron,<note place="margin">Privileg <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> for the ſupport of his Degree,<note place="margin">6. <hi>H.</hi> 6.2.</note> which they call creation money, this is ſo annexed to the Dignitie, that by no manner of alienation it can be ſevered.</p>
               <p>If the King upon ſuch Creation give land, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> untill he ſhall bee ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced to ſome other living, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Eviction to have the valew, if he be impleaded of this land by <hi>Scire fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cias,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">21. <hi>E.</hi> 3.47</note> 
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi> hee ſhall have aid of the King.</p>
               <p>If a Baron be partie to a ſuite,<note place="margin">Privileg. <hi>9.</hi> Pract. l. <hi>5.</hi> fol <hi>337.</hi> &amp; <hi>351.</hi>
                  </note> and would be eſſoigned, hee that caſts the eſſoigne out, to put in ſureties to prove the cauſe which is not uſuall in
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:57614:63"/>caſe of common perſons.</p>
               <p>In all caſes where he is to be amer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced his amerciament is not leſſe then a hundred ſhil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ings by the Statute o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Magna Charta</hi> 14. and it was to be affirmed by hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Peeres.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Privil.</hi> 10.16 <hi>E.</hi> 3 <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m.</hi> 14 38 <hi>E.</hi> 3 31 1. <hi>H.</hi> 6.7.9 <hi>H.</hi> 6 2 32. <hi>H.</hi> 6 30 19. <hi>E.</hi> 3.9.21. <hi>E</hi> 4 77 <hi>Fleta. lib.</hi> 2.</note> But for that it were troubleſome to aſſemble Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons for ſo ſmall matter, ſuch amer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciaments in time paſt have beene ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by the Barons of the Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer, who were ſometimes Barons of the Realme.</p>
               <p>Whereas by the Statute 32. <hi>H.</hi> 8. no ſubject might keepe in his family above foure Strangers borne,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Privil.</hi> 11. <hi>Br. fol.</hi> 116 <hi>Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ke</hi> 8 39. <hi>Stat.</hi> 32 <hi>H.</hi> 8.16. <hi>Privil.</hi> 12</note> yet by a <hi>Proviſo</hi> every Baron may keepe ſixe.</p>
               <p>If a Lord of the Parliament having place and voyce there,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Stat</hi> 1. <hi>E.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 13.</note> be convicted of Felony, wherein Clergie is allowed, upon requeſt, alleadging that hee is a Baron, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and clayming the benefit of his Clergie, although hee cannot reade without burning in the hand, loſſe of Inheritance or corruption of blood, hee ſhall for the firſt time bee deemed a Clerke convict, and may have purgation.</p>
               <p>Alſo,<note place="margin">Privile. <hi>13.</hi>
                  </note> whereas it is ordained that
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:57614:63"/>the Juſtice of the Peace named of the <hi>Quorum,</hi> ſhall be reſident in his Shire,<note place="margin">Stat. <hi>2.</hi> H <hi>5</hi> cap. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> by a <hi>Proviſo,</hi> the Peeres of the Realme are exampted.</p>
               <p>By the antient Lawes before <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam</hi> the <hi>Conquerors</hi> time,<note place="margin">Lemb. per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ambul. de Kent. <hi>21.</hi> Britt. cap. <hi>29.</hi> Marlb. cap <hi>10.</hi>
                  </note> every man above 12. yeeres ſhould be ſworne to the King, which we obſerve now in the veiw of <hi>Francke-pledge, Court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leete.</hi> But noble men, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are neither bound to attend the Leete nor take the oath.</p>
               <p>If an Error be brought in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon a Iudgement in <hi>B. R.</hi> the upper houſe alone without the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons,<note place="margin">Postaat. <hi>20.</hi>
                  </note> are to examine the errors.</p>
               <p>In 11. <hi>H.</hi> 6.2. in a caſe concerning diſtreſſe taken for expences and fees of the Knights of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.<note place="margin">11. <hi>H</hi> 6.2.</note> It was agreed that the Barons are not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributorie for Lands, parcell of the antient Barony, but for other lands: but there is a queſtion made whether the purchaſer of ſuch an antient Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rony ſhould enjoy the ſaid priviledge, which queſtion was not worthy the queſtioning, for as lands holden by Villaines ſervice doth not make the
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:57614:64"/>free purchaſer a Villaine, though he be bound to doe ſuch Villaine ſervice: ſo doth not ſuch Purchaſe ennoble him that purchaſeth.</p>
               <p>By the Stat. of 5. <hi>Eliz. cap</hi> 1. all Burgeſſes of Parliament ſhall take the oath of ſupremacie,<note place="margin">Sta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>5</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liz cap. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> ſo ſhall Citizens and Barons of Cinqueports, But there is a <hi>Proviſo</hi> in that Stat. that foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as the Qu. is otherwiſe ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently aſſured of the faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of the temporall lawes; Therfore this act ſhall not compellany of, or above the degree of a Baron to take this oath, nor to incurre any penalty limited for the refuſall.</p>
               <p>By the Stat. of 5. <hi>R.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 12. the King defendeth the paſſage of all manner of People in every Port,<note place="margin">Stat. <hi>5.</hi> R. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>12.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi> upon the Sea Coaſt upon paine of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiture of all their goods, except Lo. and other great men, and true and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Merchants, and the Kings ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers and all others ſhall forfeit, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But becauſe the Statute is abrogated by 4. <hi>Iacobi, c.</hi> 2. I do not ſet this down for one of the priviledges at this day; But <hi>Philip</hi> Earle of <hi>Arundell,</hi> Son of
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:57614:64"/>
                  <hi>Thomas</hi> Duke of <hi>Norfolke,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cromptons Iuriſd. <hi>31.</hi>
                  </note> was taken upon the Sea paſſing into <hi>France</hi> about 30. <hi>Eliz.</hi> and was fined in the Starre chamber, becauſe he tooke not ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pping at one of the Ports mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in that Statute.</p>
               <p>In the Priviledge before mentioned of his Clergie, it ſhall be allowed him for breaking a houſe by day or night, for robbing upon the high-way, and in all other caſes excepted in the Stat. of 1. <hi>E.</hi> 6.12. ſaving in wilfull murder and poyſoning, But in all other caſes, wherein Clergie is taken away, he is in the ſame degree with a common perſon, but the Court will not give him the benefit of this Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute, if he requireth not the ſame. If a Lord doth confeſſe his offence up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on arraignment or abjure, or is out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawed for felony, in theſe caſes it ſeemeth he may have the benefit of this Statute, <hi>viz.</hi> his Clergie, for that by the Statute of 18. <hi>Eliz. cap.</hi> 81. hee nor any other need to make purgati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,<note place="margin">Stat. <hi>18.</hi> Eliz. cap. <hi>18.</hi>
                  </note> but ſhall bee forthwith delivered out of priſon by the Juſtice. <hi>Sed quaere Bolton</hi> 202. by the Imperiall conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:57614:65"/>
                  <hi>Nobiles non torquentur in caſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, in quibus plebei torquentur nec ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenduntur, ſed decapitantur.</hi> Which forme by favour of the Prince is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed in <hi>England;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iuriſd. Br. <hi>48.</hi>
                  </note> Yet <hi>Thomas Fines,</hi> Lord <hi>Dacres,</hi> of the South. in the 37. <hi>H.</hi> 8. and the Lord <hi>Sturton</hi> 4. <hi>Mar.</hi> were hanged.</p>
               <p>By the Staute of 1. <hi>Eliz. cap.</hi> 1. for uniformitie of Common prayer,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1.</hi> Eliz cap. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> there is a <hi>proviſo,</hi> that the Baron ſhall bee tried <hi>per Pares,</hi> and not by any Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall Courts, read the Statute at large.</p>
               <p>At the Common law it was law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, for any to retaine as many Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lains as he would, but by the Statute of 21. <hi>H.</hi> 8 13. a reſtraint was made, <hi>viz.</hi> to every Archbiſhop, and Duke, ſixe Chaplains, with diſpenſation to keepe two Benefices with Cure, to every Marqueſſe or Earle five, with the like priviledge; To the Lord Chancellour, every Baron and Knight of the Garter three, with the ſame priviledge. If a Biſhop bee made an Archbiſhop, or a Baron an Earle, yet can they have but Chaplains as Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:57614:65"/>or Earle, becauſe though there be divers Dignities, yet the ſervice is to be done, but to one perſon; ſo if he be removed from his Office, in this caſe he cannot be Non-reſident with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out he procure a <hi>non obſtante.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So if a Baron retaine a Chaplaine, and before he is advanced, his Lord is attainted,<note place="margin">Cooke rep. <hi>4.117.</hi> Actons <hi>Caſe.</hi>
                  </note> as the Earle of <hi>Weſtmerland</hi> was, hee cannot accept a ſecond Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefice.</p>
               <p>Thoſe that are firſt retained, ſhall onely have priviledge in caſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By the Statute of 2. <hi>H.</hi> 5.8. that gives authoritie to the Sheriffe to raiſe <hi>Poſſe Comitat.</hi> Nevertheleſſe, may he not command the perſon of a Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to attend that ſervice, but if the Sheriff upon a <hi>ſupplicavit</hi> againſt him, returne that he is ſo puiſſant that he dare not arreſt him, the Sheriffe ſhall be grievouſly amerced for ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, for the Writ is to all Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhops, Biſhops, Dukes, Earles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and to all liege men of the County to to be ayding to him, therefore by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendment none will reſiſt the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:57614:66"/>
               <p>The words of <hi>Charta de foreſt. cap.</hi> 11. are every Archbiſhop, Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, Earle, or Baron, comming to us at our commandment and paſſing by our forreſts may take one beaſt or two by the view of the foreſter if he be preſent, or elſe he ſhall cauſe one to blow an horne that he ſeeme not to ſteale our Deare. In this Stat. though a Duke, Marqueſſe, or Viſcount, being Lord of the Parliament being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſhall have the ſame privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, ſo if the King ſend for him let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters miſſive, Meſſenger or Sergeant at arms, or by writ of <hi>Sub-paena,</hi> to appear in Chanc. they ſhall have the benefit of this Statute becauſe they came at the Kings commandement ſo in caſe of <hi>Scire facias</hi> out of the Chancery or <hi>D. R.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But if ſuch Proceſſe goe out of the <hi>C. B.</hi> to appeare before the Iuſtices or the Barons of the Exchequer he ſhall not have the benefit of the Statute, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Statute is <hi>Veniens ad nos,</hi> and in thoſe Courts they are, <hi>Quod coram nobis, &amp;c.</hi> So of the Starre-chamber. Alſo Lords that come to viſit the new
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:57614:66"/>King, though not ſent for, ſhall have the priviledge: and ſo note this Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute is a Warrant dormant and is to be vnderſtood of their returning home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <hi>Manwood, cap.</hi> 13. <hi>Crompton Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Nota.</note> 
                  <hi>D.</hi> 167. note the Statute doth give licence to kill or hunt in the Kings Parkes, though the Letter bee <hi>Tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens per forreſtam noſtram.</hi> Note that in certaine Caſes the Law doth give priviledge to the ſonnes or brethren of Noblemen, though they bee not of that degree, <hi>Stat.</hi> 21. <hi>H.</hi> 8.13. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 7. <hi>E.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 5.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Certaine Caſes wherein he hath no Priviledges.</head>
               <p>IF the King commit a Baron to pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon <hi>Durante bene placito,</hi> he cannot be diſcharged by Bayle or mainpriſe, or by the common Writ <hi>De homine replegiando.</hi> And by the ſame power it is if a noble perſon bee committed by the Kings Councell, for they are incorporated to his Highneſſe, and doe command, as with the Kings mouth: and the ſame law is, if a Nobleman be
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:57614:67"/>committed to priſon by the abſolute Commandment of the Kings Jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, ſitting in their place of Judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,<note place="margin">Stam. lib <hi>2.</hi> cap <hi>18.</hi> fol. <hi>72.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Stamf. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 18. <hi>fol.</hi> 72. as you have before, when the Prince himſelfe by the chiefe Juſtice ſitting in the Kings Bench, and was not bay leable. Alſo a Capias and an Exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent may be awarded upon an Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a felony.</p>
               <p>This Statute of Praemunire, <hi>cap.</hi> 1.16. <hi>R,</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. upon which Statute an Abbot which was Lord of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, being impleaded, did pray pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge to appeare by attorney, <hi>Et per Curiam,</hi> could not for a <hi>Ceſſavit</hi> lyeth againſt him.</p>
               <p>Upon contempt of Peeres a <hi>Capias</hi> may bee awarded, 1. <hi>H.</hi> 5. <hi>ult.</hi> 27. <hi>H.</hi> 8.22.</p>
               <p>If he depart the Realme as Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadour, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and returne not at the Kings commandement, the King may ſeize his lands and goods, <hi>Dyer</hi> 108.176. The Dutches of <hi>Suffolkes</hi> caſe, if he impriſon any man in his houſe, whereupon there is a writ <hi>De homine replegiando,</hi> if he convey him from the
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:57614:67"/>Sheriffe the Court will award a <hi>Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thernam</hi> to arreſt,<note place="margin">11. <hi>H.</hi> 4.15</note> and impriſon him till he deliver the priſoner.</p>
               <p>All Lords are compellable to take the oath mentioned in the Statute 3. <hi>Iacobi,</hi> and ſee the Statute of 7. <hi>Iacobi,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">3. <hi>Iac. ca.</hi> 4. 7 <hi>Ia. cap.</hi> 6.</note> who hav eauthoritie to adminiſter it unto them.</p>
               <p>Being arraigned of felony in an Appeale, he ſhall not be tried by his Peeres, as in caſe of Inditement, in which caſe he may not challenge any of the Triers, either peremptorily or upon cauſes which is permitted to all other common perſons.</p>
               <p>The Iudgment is the vſuall Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment given againſt common perſons, and though the King pardon all but the loſſe of his head, that is of ſpeciall grace not <hi>ex debito.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By Attainder the blood is corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and he and his poſterity made ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noble,<note place="margin">Stam. lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>34.</hi>
                  </note> and cannot be reſtored by the Kings pardon, but onely by authoritie of Parliament.</p>
               <p>And note that Nobility is not a thing ſubſtantiall, but meerely acciden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall preſent or abſent without corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:57614:68"/>of his ſubject, for experience ſhewes that honourable titles are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained by exorbitant crimes, when the nature in the meane while cannot be thruſt out with a forke, wherefore though we tearme extinguiſhment of Nobility in caſes of Attainder, yet this phraſe is not vſed as though Nobility were eſſentially in the homour of the blood more then any other hereditary faculty; But becauſe the right of inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance which deſcends by communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of blood, is by that meanes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined, and alſo in regard of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation of the crime, it is called cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of blood, 16. <hi>Eliz. Dyer</hi> 332. The Lord <hi>Charles Flowards</hi> caſe, if one be made a Knight by a forraign King, he is ſo to be ſtiled in all legall procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings in this Realme, But if he be crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Emperour an Earle, it is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wiſe, <hi>Coke</hi> 7.16.</p>
               <p>If the King Create the ſon a Duke, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and the father dies, he within age ſhal be in ward, but if he had bin made a Knight in his f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>hers life, he ſhould not be in ward, neither for the lands deſcended, nor marriage, <hi>Coke</hi> 74.
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:57614:68"/>
                  <hi>Drueries</hi> Caſe, though he be within age.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Nobilitie and Lords in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation onely.</head>
               <p>THere be other Lords in reputation and appellation, who neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe are not <hi>Iure,</hi> neither can they enjoy the priviledges of thoſe of the Nobilitie of the Parliament <hi>(viz.)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Sonne and heire of a Duke, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the life of his father, is onely by curteſie called an Earle, and the eldeſt ſonne of an Ea. a Baron, but not in le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall proceedings <hi>Br.</hi> Treaſon 2.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Coke</hi> 8-16.</note> But the King may create them in the life of their Aunceſtors Lords of the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament.</p>
               <p>A Duke or other of the Nobilitie of a forraign Nation being named Duke in Letters of ſafe conduct, that makes him not Duke to be ſued by that name in <hi>England,</hi> but a forraigne King ought ſo to be ſtiled, though he hath not <hi>merum imperium</hi> out of his owne Kingdome <hi>Cok</hi> 7.15. <hi>&amp;c,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All the younger Sonnes of the King
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:57614:69"/>of <hi>England</hi> are Earles by birth with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out other creation, and onely Lords by reputation,</p>
               <p>A Lord of <hi>Ireland</hi> or <hi>Scotland,</hi> though he be <hi>poſt-natus,</hi> is but onely Lord in reputation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Noble Women.</head>
               <p>ALthough Noble Women may not ſit in Parliament in reſpect of their Sexes, yet are they in Law Peeres of the Realme, and may chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge all,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Coke</hi> 8.53.</note> or moſt of the former Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges.</p>
               <p>But the opinions of ſome have been,<note place="margin">Crompt. Iuſt de peace <hi>85.</hi>
                  </note> that they cannot maintaine any Action upon the Statute of 2. <hi>R.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. <hi>de Scand. Magnat.</hi> becauſe the Statute ſpeakes onely of other Sexes.</p>
               <p>If any of the Kings ſervants with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in in the Checkroll conſpire the death of any Noble woman, that is not felo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny within the Statute of 3. H. 7.13.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Honourable women of three ſorts.</head>
               <p>By Creation, Deſcent, Marriage.</p>
               <pb n="133" facs="tcp:57614:69"/>
               <p> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
                  <hi>H.</hi> 8. Created <hi>Anne Bullen</hi> Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſſe of <hi>Pembrooke,</hi> &amp; King <hi>James</hi> Created the Lady <hi>Compton,</hi> Wife to Sir <hi>Thomas Compton,</hi> Counteſſe of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> in the life of her ſaid Husband without any addition of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to him. And formerly by Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents openly read in Parliament with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any other inveſture did Create <hi>Mary</hi> ſole Daughter and heire of the late Baron of <hi>Aburgauen.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Camden</hi> 63.6.</note> 
                  <hi>Baroneſſe de le Spenſer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Noble Women by Deſcent are thoſe to whom lands holden by ſuch Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie doe deſcend, or whoſe Anceſtors were ſeized of an eſtate deſcendable in their Titles of Dukedomes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or thoſe whoſe Anceſtors were ſummo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the Parliament, by this an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance doth accrue to their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteritie.</p>
               <p> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> They who take to Husband any Peere of the Realme, though they themſelves were not noble; <hi>Forteſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cue, fol.</hi> 100.</p>
               <p>Queſtion hath bin made whether the Dignitie of one ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moned to the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament dying without iſſue male may
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:57614:70"/>deſcend to the female, but this may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by the former Treatiſe.</p>
               <p>Concerning the title of Honour de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendable to the Heire female, it is cleere that ſuch offices being of eſtate of inheritance doe deſcend, as the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of the high Conſtableſhip of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> challenged <hi>tempore H.</hi> 3. by the Duke of <hi>Buckingham</hi> was adjudged to deſcend to the Daughter of <hi>Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frey Bohun</hi> Earle of <hi>Hereford.</hi> So the office of Earle Marſhall deſcended to the houſe of <hi>Norfolke,</hi> all which offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are as unfit to be exerciſed by their ſexes, as unfit for them to be ſummo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the Parliament.</p>
               <p>And if ſuch Title come in competi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the iſſue ſhall bee tried by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, and certified by the Kings Writ, and not by Jury, <hi>Coke</hi> 6.5 3.7. <hi>part</hi> 15.</p>
               <p>Though all Daughters be Coperce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and make but one Heire, yet in deſcent of Dignities it is otherwiſe, for they bee things entire, participa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of ſuperioritie, therefore deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable onely to the eldeſt. And ſo is the Civill Law, yet there was a Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:57614:70"/>
                  <hi>tempore H.</hi> 3. touching the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent of the Earledome of <hi>Cheſter,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Obijt. <hi>17.</hi> H. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> the Earle dying without iſſue, leaving his Siſters his Heires; The Judgement was that it ſhould be divided equally among Coperceners; But this Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was held erroneous in that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry age, <hi>Vide Bract. li.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 34, <hi>fol.</hi> 76. <hi>hoc fuit injuſtum, &amp;c.</hi> His reaſons are, becauſe the honour of Chivalrie, chiefly conſiſting in the Nobilitie may not be divided: for by multitude of partitions, the reputation of Honours in ſuch ſucceſſion muſt bee impaired, and the ſtrength of the Realme being drawne into many hands by ſuch par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition much infeebled. In which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution <hi>Britton</hi> by commandment, and in the name of <hi>E.</hi> 1. accorded <hi>fol.</hi> 187. The former Judgement was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven about 17. <hi>H.</hi> 3. And the Writers of that time teſtifie, that it came holy unto <hi>Iohn Scot,</hi> Son of <hi>David</hi> Earle of <hi>Huntington,</hi> and <hi>Anguiſh</hi> and <hi>Maude</hi> the eldeſt Siſter of the ſaid <hi>Randolph,</hi> if it were given upon the death of <hi>John Scot,</hi> who died without iſſue about 24. H. 3. yet it ſtood in force,
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:57614:71"/>becauſe the King aſſumed the Earle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to himſelfe upon other ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction to the coperceners, <hi>Mat. Par.</hi> 366. <hi>tamen vide Mills</hi> 75. <hi>&amp; Guillem</hi> 28.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hugh Lupus</hi> the firſt Earle of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> was by the Conquerour his vncle created into that dignitie,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mills</hi> 74.75. <hi>Coke</hi> 35.7 <hi>part</hi> 15.</note> 
                  <hi>habend. fibi, &amp;c. adeo libere per gladi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um ſicut Rex ipſe tenuit Angliam per Coronam, &amp;c.</hi> he died without iſſue, and the Earldome divided among his 4. ſiſters. If ſhe be noble by birth, though ſhe marry vnder her degree, ſhe remaines noble, but thoſe innobled by marriage, and after marry with a man of meaner degree, utterly loſe her former dignitie, <hi>Forteſcue</hi> 100. <hi>Cooke</hi> 6.33.4.118.</p>
               <p>It was the caſe of <hi>Ra. Howard</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſquire, husband of the widow of the Lord <hi>Powes</hi> againſt the Dutches of <hi>Suffolke,</hi> the Writ naming her Ladie <hi>Anne Powes, Dyer</hi> 79. ſo alſo in Qu. <hi>Maryes</hi> times when the Dutches of <hi>Suffolke</hi> married <hi>Stokes bre. Bro.</hi> 146. digeſt <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Tit.</hi> 9. for the dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity accruing by marriage is but in
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:57614:71"/>fait and not by any record, <hi>Coke</hi> 6.53. <hi>Coke</hi> 4.117. <hi>Cawells inſtit. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Tit.</hi> 10.15.</p>
               <p>So long ſhall a Dukes wife be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Dutches, and an Earles Counteſſe, and enjoy all honours appertaining to that eſtate, with taſting, kneeling, ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And a Baroneſſe and Knights wife ſaluted Lady, <hi>Quamdiu matrimonium aut viduitas vxoris du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant,</hi> except ſhe elope, for as then every woman ſhall loſe her dower, ſo being advanced by titles of dignitie by that husband by ſuch elopement lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth them.</p>
               <p>If a Ladie which is married come through the forreſt, ſhee hath no priviledge by the Statute, but a Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſſe or Counteſſe during the time ſhe is vnmarried may, <hi>Crompt. Juriſ dict.</hi> 167.</p>
               <p>Such Ladies whether they be mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried or ſole upon Indictment, ſhall be tried <hi>per Peeres</hi> by the Statute of 20. <hi>H.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 9. it being a declaration of the common law.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Coke</hi> 6.52.</note>
               </p>
               <p>By the Civill Law, <hi>Si filia Regis nubat alicui Domino, vel Comit. dicetur
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:57614:72"/>tamen ſemper Regalis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Among Noble women there is diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of degrees, and according to their qualities, the law gives ſpeciall priviledges as followeth by the Stat. of 25. of <hi>E.</hi> 3, 2. it is high Treaſon to compaſſe or imagine the death of the Queene, or to violate the Kings com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion.</p>
               <p>The Kings Spouſe is a ſole perſon in law to purchaſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> plead and be impleaded, <hi>Coke</hi> 4.23.6. <hi>Theboal lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 4 24 <hi>E.</hi> 3.3.8. <hi>Bract.</hi> 363. And of ſuch acts of Parliament as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne her, the Iudges ought to take notice, <hi>Coment.</hi> 231. a <hi>Coke</hi> 8.28. In ſome caſes ſhe ſhall have Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive as the King himſelfe. See the caſe of Wardſhip 5. E. 3.4. <hi>Stamf. prerog. cap.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>The Qu. Wife to the King, or widow, ſhall not be amerced if ſhe be non-ſuited, whereas all other ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects ſhall, for ſhe ſhall participate with the Kings prerogative, <hi>Coke</hi> 8.62. but not in all caſes, for the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject ſhall not ſue to her by Petition as to the King, 11. <hi>H.</hi> 4 67. <hi>Stamf. pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rog. cap.</hi> 22.</p>
               <pb n="139" facs="tcp:57614:72"/>
               <p>Againſt the King, <hi>Nullum tempus occurrit,</hi> otherwiſe of the Queene 18. <hi>E.</hi> 3.2. <hi>Philippa Regina Angl. Ibid. fol.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 13. <hi>Stam. prerog.</hi> 18.</p>
               <p>In 21. <hi>E.</hi> 3.6. A Protection was allowed againſt the Queene.</p>
               <p>In a Writ of dower againſt <hi>Iſabel</hi> Qu. of <hi>England</hi> mother to the then King, the Iudges were of opinion that ſhee was not to anſwer to any Writ, but ſaid they to the plaintife it behoveth you to go to her by Petition, to whom the Demandant <hi>Dixit graits,</hi> and prayed the court for a continuance of the action vntill ſhee might ſpeake with the Queene; But they nor the Queenes Councell would agree that, the Qu. ſhould be accepted as anſwerable 10. <hi>E</hi> 3.379.</p>
               <p>The Wife of the Kings eldeſt Son hath ſome prerogative not communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable to the Wives of other Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, for by the Statute of 25. <hi>E.</hi> 3. It is high Treaſon to violate her.</p>
               <p>Dutcheſſes alſo and Counteſſes have ſpeciall honour appertaining to their eſtates, as kneeling and taſting, which things I leave to the Heraulds.</p>
               <pb n="140" facs="tcp:57614:73"/>
               <p>The Statute of 7. <hi>Iac. cap.</hi> 6. intitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led an Act for the adminiſtring the oath of Allegiance requireth thoſe of 18. yeares or above to take the ſaid oath. The title is for adminiſtration of the Oath, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and reformation of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried women Recuſants.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Ladyes in Reputation.</head>
               <p>THe Wife or Widow of the ſonne, and heire of a Duke or Earle, in the life of his Father, is a Lady by Curteſie, and taketh place according to the antient time, as they have beene permitted by their Soveraigne Prince, and allowance of the Herauld. But in legall proceedings they are not to have ſuch Priviledge.</p>
               <p>If a Noblewoman of <hi>Spaine</hi> come into <hi>England</hi> by a ſafe conduct, or, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And ſo ſtiled in the ſaid Letters, yet is ſhee but a Lady in reputation.</p>
               <p>And Engliſh woman borne, taketh to Husband a Spaniſh or French Duke, though hee be made Denizen, yet ſhall ſhe not beare the title of Dignitie in legall proceedings.</p>
               <pb n="141" facs="tcp:57614:73"/>
               <p>A German woman is married to the Marqueſſe of <hi>Northampton,</hi> or, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> unleſſe ſhe be made Denizen, ſhee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not claime the priviledge or title of her Husband, no more then ſhee can claime Dower or Joynture.</p>
               <p>An Engliſh woman doth take the Earle of <hi>Kildare</hi> in <hi>Ireland</hi> to her Husband, or if a Lord in <hi>Scotland,</hi> though hee be <hi>poſt natus, &amp;c.</hi> their wives ſhall not aprticipate their Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands Dignities.</p>
               <p>But if the King Create one of his Subjects naturalized by Parliament to be Viſcount <hi>Rocheſter</hi> within <hi>England,</hi> and after ſummon him to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by Writ, and aſſigne him place there, by this is he made Peere of the Realme, and partakes with them of all Priviledges, and by conſequence his Wife, Widow and Children af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him,<note place="margin">E. <hi>of</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus <hi>in</hi> Scotland.</note> 34. <hi>E.</hi> 3.35. <hi>Gilbert Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frevils caſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But if an Engliſh man be made by the Emperour, Earle of the Empire, his Wife ſhall not beare that title, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther according to law or reputation.</p>
               <p>All Daughters of Dukes, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſes
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:57614:74"/>and Earles, are (by cuſtome long uſed in the Kings Palace) to be named Ladies, and to have preceden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie according to the degrees of their parents, and of this cuſtome the Law taketh notice.</p>
               <p>But nevertheleſſe in the Kings Courts of Juſtice, they beare not this title of Honour, no more then the Sons of ſuch noble perſonages. Brothers to ſuch Ladyes may doe.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="question">
            <pb n="143" facs="tcp:57614:74"/>
            <head>The Hypotheſis or particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Queſtion.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hether the Dignitie of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgavenny, Sit conjuncta feodo,</hi> and ſuch as ought to deſcend to the ſpeciall Heire male ſeized of the Caſtle, bearing the head of that Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and of the lands that make that Honour.</p>
            <p>Or whether the Dignitie, Name and Stile, to be Baron of <hi>Aburgaven.</hi> ought to deſcend to the generall Heire male, who is not intereſſed in the ſaid Caſtle or honour.</p>
            <p>For the more orderly proceeding herein to avoid confuſion, and that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thing appeare concerning his que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion in his proper perſon. There ſhall be ſhewed,</p>
            <p>Firſt, that the Barony is a Barony by by tenure, a very antient Honour, and
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:57614:75"/>no Barony by Writ onely, whereof will enſue by the former Declaration in the treatiſe of Barony; That the dignitie and name <hi>de jure</hi> ought to go and deſcend with the Caſtle and Honour ſo holden, as long as the ſame ſhall or may continue in the name, blood, and line of ſuch as are nobly deſcended, and may ſupport the ſame. There ſhall be Proved</p>
            <p> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, That the ſaid Barony of <hi>Aburgav.</hi> and the name, title, and dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of Lord, and Barony of <hi>Aburg. de facto</hi> hath come and deſcended with the Caſtle, which make the honour of by the ſpace of 300. yeeres laſt paſt, in their noble Families in the blood of the <hi>Haſtings.</hi> 2. In the time of <hi>Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>champe,</hi> and the time of <hi>Nevill,</hi> where the name by the Grace of God doth now, and long may continue, every which family having right to the ſaid Caſtle and honour, did lawfully beare the name and title of Lord <hi>Aburgav.</hi> and had place in Parliament accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly. And therein ſhall be anſwered the objections made to the contrary.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="145" facs="tcp:57614:75"/>
               <head>That the Barony of <hi>Aburgavenny</hi> is a Barony by Tenure, and an antient Honour.</head>
               <p>AFter the <hi>Normans</hi> had conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red this Land, it was carefully obſerved by them as a matter of much moment, and a point of ſpecial policie to place upon the confines or borders of the Brittaines or Welch, not then ſubdued, men of much matter, not onely ſufficiently able to encounter the inrodes and invaſions of the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, but alſo willing to make onſet on them, and to enlarge the conqueſt. Theſe men thus placed were of high blood, credit, and continuance among them, countreymen to the <hi>Normans,</hi> and in whoſe faith, and prowes the Conquerors repoſed ſpeciall confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and truſt. And therfore in the territories given unto them to hold, the tenures were deviſed to be very ſpeciall and of great importance, and their Honours inriched with many priviledges,<note place="margin">7. <hi>H</hi> 6.35. 18 <hi>E</hi> 2. <hi>Aſſiſis</hi> 382 <hi>Fol.</hi>
                  </note> The Earle of <hi>Cheſter</hi> for the North border of <hi>Wales</hi> erected a County <hi>Palatine;</hi> And the Barons of
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:57614:76"/>the middle part of the South Marches were adorned i a manner with a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latine Juriſdiction, having a Court of Chancery, and Writs onely among themſelves pleadable, to the intent that their attendance, might not thence be driven, for the proſecuting of Controverſies or quarrels in the Law. And as for the other part of the South Marches, they ſeemed ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently fenced with the River of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verne and the Sea.</p>
               <p>The Caſtle of <hi>Aburgavenny</hi> taketh his name from the River of <hi>Gevenny,</hi> whereon it is ſcituate, and the Brittiſh word <hi>Abber,</hi> which ſignifieth a Mouth, and is interpreted the Mouth of <hi>Gevenny,</hi> becauſe the Caſtle and Mouth of <hi>Aburgavenny</hi> is built neere the place where the ſaid River of <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venny</hi> doth open it ſelfe to the end of the Uske; It is an antient Fortreſſe of old foundation: there or neere unto the place (as learned men doe proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, and upon many good circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces conjecture) where the Romans builded their <hi>Gabonium.</hi> It is the chiefeſt Townes of the County, called
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:57614:76"/>the higher <hi>Guent,</hi> by the Romans cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Ventum Gallinum,</hi> now parcell of the County of <hi>Monmouth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Caſtle, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> was firſt given to be holden <hi>Per Baroniam ſive grand Serjantie,</hi> the ſervice whereof is of great importance, as appeareth by this Record following.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Inquiſitio capt &amp;c.</hi> At <hi>Aburgaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ex bu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>delle Eſch <hi>6.</hi> E <hi>2.</hi> Mar. Wal.</note>6. <hi>E.</hi> 2. upon the death of <hi>Jobn Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtings</hi> found <hi>quod idem Iohannes tenuit caſtrum, &amp;c. De Rege in Capite per ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vicium homagij wardi maritag. cum acciderit, &amp; ſi <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> fuerit inter Regem Angl. &amp; Principem Walliae dict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Iohannes debet cuſtodire patriam de Operwent ſumptibus proprijs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Inquiſitio capt. apud Hereford</hi> upon a Writ of <hi>ad quod damnum,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ex Bun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dell. Eſch. <hi>25.</hi> E. <hi>3.</hi> Ex rot. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent. <hi>4.</hi> E. <hi>1.</hi> num. <hi>36.</hi>
                  </note> found <hi>quod non eſt ad damnum Regis nec, &amp;c. ſi Rex conce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>at Priori, &amp;c. de Aburg. quod ipſe duas acr. prat. vocat Weldelham, &amp;c. quas de Lorentio de Haſtings nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Comit. Pembrooke poſt Statutum de Mortmaine retinere poſſit ſibi &amp; Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoribus ſuis, &amp; dicunt quod praed.</hi> 2. <hi>acr. fuerunt de dominicis praedicti Comit. &amp; tenentur immediate de Rege ut parcella
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:57614:77"/>Caſtri quod tenetur de eo, &amp; de nullo alio.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Alſo, that this Barony was of a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry large Seignorie, and had petty Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons or Baronets holding thereof ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth by Writ, 1. <hi>E.</hi> 1. for the more ſpeedy gathering of 15<hi rend="sup">th</hi> which was granted to him, towards his charge to the Holy land, which Writ is dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to the Tenants of the ſaid Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, that they ſhould pay their part to <hi>Gremball Poneefote,</hi> and <hi>Henry de Bray</hi> appointed Collectours, directed in this manner.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rex Abbatibus Prior. Baron. Mil. li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beris hominbius &amp; omnibus alijs Tenen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus de honor. Aberg. Salut. Cum Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiepiſcopi, Epiſcopi, Abbat. Prior. Mil. &amp; omnes alij de regno</hi> 15<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. <hi>de bonis ſuis, qnibuſdam tamen rebus exceptis nobis liberaliter conceſſerunt &amp; benigne ad exonerationem debitorum in quibus di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſis mercatoribus de tempore quo mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram in terra ſancta geſſimus obligamur, Nos, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſer. </seg>2</label> 
                  <hi>Obſervatio ſecunda,</hi> that the Title of <hi>Aberga. de facto</hi> hath deſcended with the Caſtle, &amp;c.</p>
               <pb n="149" facs="tcp:57614:77"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>William</hi> Conquerour gave the County of higher <hi>Guent,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hamline de Backlune.</note> unto <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line de Backlune,</hi> the Sonne of <hi>Drugo de Backlune</hi> a Norman, which buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Caſtle and Priory of <hi>Aberga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venny,</hi> and after aſſured the ſame to <hi>Brian</hi> de <hi>Wallingford,</hi> Sonne of <hi>Eudo</hi> Earle of <hi>Brittaine,</hi> Sonne of <hi>Lucie</hi> younger Siſter of the ſaid <hi>Hamline,</hi> by whom it was conveyed to <hi>Walter</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Sonne of <hi>Miles</hi> of <hi>Glouceſter,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">tralt. <hi>of</hi> Glou. Brewes.</note> Earle of <hi>Hereford,</hi> from him it came to his Brother <hi>Henry,</hi> and thence to the Families of <hi>Brewes</hi> Barons in the Marches of <hi>Wales,</hi> and from them to <hi>Cantelupe,</hi> Barons in the ſaid Marches.<note place="margin">Cantelupe.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The the line of Hastings, owners of this Caſtle, and in reſpect thereof intituled, Barons of Aburgavenny.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>GEorge de Cantelupe</hi> Baron of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgavenny</hi> and <hi>Cant.</hi> the laſt of that name died without iſſue having two Siſters,<note place="margin">Haſtings.</note> 
                  <hi>Ioan</hi> the eldeſt married to <hi>Henry Haſtings</hi> and <hi>Milliſcent,</hi> married to <hi>Eudo la Zouch. Henry Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtings</hi> by his had iſſue <hi>Iohn,</hi> and becauſe
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:57614:78"/>he did adhere to the Barons <hi>tempore H.</hi> 3. hee was impriſoned for ſeven yeeres,<note place="margin">Ed. Kelen Article <hi>35.</hi> Rot. Cart. H <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> during which time hee died. And that Barony being in the Kings hands, he gave it to <hi>Peter de Sabandia</hi> in exchange for the Mannor of <hi>Bayden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall</hi> parcell of the Honour of <hi>Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond</hi> which the ſaid King had given him; So that this Barony came now to the Earle of <hi>Richmond,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſc <hi>8.</hi> E. <hi>3.</hi> In Suffex. Ex rot. clauſ. <hi>2.</hi> E. <hi>1</hi> indoeſ. memb. <hi>12.</hi>
                  </note> as by an office found after the death of <hi>Iohn Britton</hi> Earle of <hi>Richmond, tempore E.</hi> 3. appeareth.</p>
               <p>The ſaid <hi>Iohn Haſtings</hi> at the time of the death of <hi>Henry</hi> his Father, and <hi>Joan</hi> his mother, both which died in the life of the ſaid <hi>Geo. Cant.</hi> as alſo at the time of the death of the ſaid <hi>Geo.</hi> his Uncle was within age, and in ward to <hi>E.</hi> 1. during whoſe mino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, there was a partition betweene the ſaid <hi>Milliſcent</hi> his Aunt, and the ſaid <hi>Iohn,</hi> by which the Caſtle, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of <hi>Aberg.</hi> then extended to the yeerely value of two hundred pounds, eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene ſhillings and three pence, as alſo <hi>Kill Garren,</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Cleere,</hi> and other lands in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales.</hi> And unto the
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:57614:78"/>ſaid <hi>Milliſcent</hi> were allotted the Caſtle of <hi>Totnes</hi> in <hi>Devon, &amp;c. Eyton</hi> in the County of <hi>Bedford,</hi> and <hi>Farringworth, &amp;c.</hi> with divers other lands.</p>
               <p>The ſaid <hi>Iohn</hi> came to full age,<note place="margin">the firſt <hi>Iohn Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtings,</hi> Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg.</hi>
                  </note> 11. <hi>E.</hi> 1. and did his homage, and had his Livery as appeareth by Record, but by the ſame Record appeareth, that the Barony of <hi>Haſtings</hi> was never redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med according to the Edict <hi>Kellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth,</hi> but granted to <hi>Peter de Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandia,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Clauſ <hi>11.</hi> E. <hi>1.</hi> Mem. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>This <hi>Iohn</hi> did lawfully beare the Title of Lord <hi>Abergavenny,</hi> by this partition.</p>
               <p>The ſaid <hi>John</hi> being one of the Competitors for the Crowne of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> with the reſt ſubmitted him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe 19. <hi>E.</hi> 1. to the determination of the ſaid King as Supreame Lord of <hi>Scotland,</hi> which Commiſſion was fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in theſe words:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A tout crus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In magno Rot. Sca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>r.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp;c. Florence Comit. de Holland, Robert de Bruſe, ſeigneur de Vaſdaum. Io. Balioll Seigneur de Bade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naw, Patrick de Dumbar, Comite de la March, Ia. de Vaſcye pur ſon pier Nich, de Seules, Gulielm. de Roſſe: Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:57614:79"/>en dieu cum nous entendomus daver droit en Roylme de Eſcoce, &amp; cel duel jure chalenger &amp; avouer devant ceo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> pluis de pouer, juriſdiction &amp; reaſon eiſt de trier noſtre droit. Et le noble Prince Seig. Edward, &amp;c. nous ſyant en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme per bo. &amp; ſufficient reaſon<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> a luy come aver droit Soveraigne Su<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>r se<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> du dit Roylme de Eſcoce, &amp; la Conu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance d'oyer trier &amp; determin. noſtre droit, nous ne noſtre volunt ſans nul ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner de force ou diſtreſſe de droit devant luy come Soveraigne Su<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>r de la terre, &amp;c. l'an de grace,</hi> 1291.</p>
               <p> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> There was another like writing, whereby theſe competitors doe yeeld ſome of the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſaid <hi>E.</hi> 1. untill he ſhould deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the controverſie.</p>
               <p> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> After the ſentence given by <hi>E.</hi> 1. for <hi>John Balioll,</hi> who afterwards adhered to the French againſt <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whereupon <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. proſecuting war againſt <hi>Scotland,</hi> the Pope intermed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, a Parliament was proclaimed to be held at <hi>Lincolne.</hi> 29. <hi>E.</hi> 1. where it wass agreed that the King ſhould write to the Pope touching his right
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:57614:79"/>to that Crowne, and the wrong offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him. And that the Nobility ſhould write, that they neither could, nor ought to ſuffer,<note place="margin">Nota</note> that the King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> ſhould referre the ſame to the Popes ſentence, they ſubſcribing their names and titles of Honour, among which was the ſaid <hi>Iohn Haſtings</hi> name in this manner, <hi>Iohannes Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus de Aburgavenny.</hi>
               </p>
               <p> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> In 16. <hi>E.</hi> 1. the King purpoſing to go to <hi>France,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ex Rot. mal. <hi>17.</hi> E <hi>1.</hi> in dorſ.</note> charged the Lords Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of <hi>Wales</hi> to be reſident upon their Baronies, fearing the invaſion of the <hi>Welch.</hi> and <hi>Anno</hi> 17. in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion of <hi>Riſe ap Meredocke</hi> the King being in <hi>France,</hi> directeth his Writ unto the ſaid Marchers under the <hi>Teſt. Edmundi fratris ſui.</hi> And among other the Barons there named as <hi>Ed. de Mortimer, Roger Mortimer, Pet. Corbet. Roger le Strange, Fulk Fitz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warren, Galfrid de Canmyl, William Mortimer, Guy de Brian, Iohn de Haſtings, Ra. de Tony, William de Bruſe, Iohn Tregouſe, Bogok Nevill, Ric. Fiz-Allen, &amp; Io. Fitz-Reginald,</hi> and all Barons Marchers.</p>
               <pb n="154" facs="tcp:57614:80"/>
               <p> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Againe 20. <hi>E.</hi> 1. When therer was a great quarrell between <hi>Gilbert de Clare,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">20. E. 1.14 <hi>in recept. Scacar.</hi>
                  </note> Earle of <hi>Glouceſter</hi> and <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> and <hi>Humfrey de Bohum,</hi> late E. of <hi>Hereford</hi> and <hi>Eſſex,</hi> whereupon murders, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> had beene committed in their lands in <hi>Brecnocke.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A Commiſſion was awarded to the Biſhop of <hi>Ely, William de Valence,</hi> the Kings vncle, <hi>Io. de Mettingham</hi> one of the Iudges, and unto <hi>Robert de Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> to heare and determine the ſame. In which Commiſſion the ſaid <hi>Iohn Haſtings</hi> was one In which the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners would have had the ſaid Barons to have beene ſworne to make preſentment thereof, which they refuſed, ſtanding upon their privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and therfore the Enqueſt was impannelled of others.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>P.</hi> 23. <hi>E.</hi> 1. The ſaid <hi>Iohn</hi> was ſummoned ot the Parliament,<note place="margin">Som. Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liamen. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no <hi>24.</hi> E. <hi>1.</hi> Som. Parl. a. <hi>35.</hi> E. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> which was to be holden the Sunday next after the feaſt of St. <hi>Martin,</hi> as alſo to a Parliament at <hi>Carlile,</hi> 35. <hi>E.</hi> 1.</p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="Object." n="1"/>
               <p>It will be objected that <hi>Iohn</hi> his father was ſummoned in 49. <hi>H.</hi> 3. and therfore in regard thereof and not
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:57614:80"/>in reſpect of this Barony was this <hi>Iohn ſummoned.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is true that <hi>Henry Haſtings</hi> was ſummoned it 49. <hi>H</hi> 3. he was Captaine of the Caſte of <hi>Killingworth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reſpon.</note> and held it againſt the King, and beheaded the Kings Meſſenger ſent unto him, for the which fact was the ſaid impriſonment before ſpoken of;<note place="margin">Ed. Kenel. act <hi>34.</hi> Cron. Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenſ.</note> And the Barony of <hi>Haſtings</hi> deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded not to the ſaid <hi>John.</hi> Therfore in the letters to the Pope, and in his claime to <hi>Scotland</hi> he writeth himſelfe <hi>Iohannes Haſtings, &amp;c.</hi> and not <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Haſtings</hi> which if that title had belonged to him he had expreſſed it.</p>
               <p> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>2</label> That he uſed the Title of <hi>Dominus Abergav.</hi> as <hi>Dominus Proprietarius,</hi> and not as <hi>Dominus Honorarius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſame may be ſaid of the other Competitor, and the Letters to the Pope which were ridiculous.</p>
               <p>In the Summons 23. <hi>E.</hi> 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Io. Hastings Mil.</hi> and not <hi>Iohan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes Dominus Haſtings,</hi> therefore,<note place="margin">Reſpon.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>3</label> They uſed not then to expreſſe the place except for diſtinction. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="156" facs="tcp:57614:81"/>
               <head>Now to the Deſcent.</head>
               <p>THis <hi>Iolin</hi> died,<note place="margin">Continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent.</note> 6. <hi>E.</hi> 2. having iſſue <hi>Iohn,</hi> who died 18 <hi>E.</hi> 2. And in the <hi>Diem eligit extremum,</hi> he is ſtiled <hi>Johannes Haſtings, Dominus de Aber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gav.</hi> and Earle of <hi>Pembrooke, tempore E.</hi> 3. he died 12. <hi>E.</hi> 3. having iſſue <hi>Iohn</hi> his Heire,<note place="margin">Ex bundel. Eſc. <hi>18.</hi> E. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> Earle of <hi>Pembrooke,</hi> and Lord of <hi>Abergav.</hi> who died 49. <hi>E.</hi> 3. having iſſue <hi>Iohn</hi> Earle of <hi>Pem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brooke,</hi> &amp;c. who died by reaſon of a wound received at a Juſt at <hi>Wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtocke</hi> about 13. <hi>R.</hi> 2. he was the laſt of that name, Baron of <hi>Aburgavenny.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Family of <hi>Beauchampe.</hi> Lord Aburgavenny.</head>
               <p>AFter the death of the ſaid <hi>Iohn,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Peauchamp <hi>Lord of</hi> Aberg.</note> 
                  <hi>Reginald Gray,</hi> Lord <hi>Richyn,</hi> Sonne of <hi>Elizabeth</hi> Siſter of the ſaid <hi>Iohn</hi> the great Grandfather of him that laſt died, claimed this Barony, and thereof had Livery. And thereupon grew a contention concerning the bearing of the Armes of <hi>Haſtings</hi>
                  <pb n="157" facs="tcp:57614:81"/>without difference betweene the Lo. <hi>Gray</hi> of the whole blood, and Sir <hi>Edward Haſtings</hi> of the halfe blood, which was adjudged for the Lord <hi>Gray</hi> in the Earle Marſhalls Court.</p>
               <p>A like contention was betweene the Lord <hi>Gray</hi> and <hi>William Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>champe,</hi> third ſonne of <hi>Thomas</hi> the el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Earle of <hi>Warwicke,</hi> who claimed this Barony againſt the ſaid Lord <hi>Gray</hi> by vertue of an intaile from the ſaid <hi>John</hi> the elder, which proved, and upon Compoſition the ſaid <hi>Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nald</hi> 15. <hi>R.</hi> 2. levied a Fine to,<note place="margin">M. <hi>15.</hi> R. <hi>2</hi> &amp; recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dat. Term. H. prox.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi> whereby he acknowledged the right of the ſaid Caſtle, to the uſe of the ſaid <hi>William Beauchampe,</hi> as by an old Mſſs remaining with the Earle of <hi>Kent</hi> may appeare,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> the Earle of <hi>Kents</hi> booke.</note> as alſo by a partiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſaid Lands.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
